<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conference betvvixt a mother a devout recusant, and her sonne a zealous protestant seeking by humble and dutifull satisfaction to winne her vnto the trueth, and publike worship of god established nowe in England. Gathered by him whose hearts desire is, that all may come to the knowledge of God, and be saued.</title>
            <title>Conference betwixt a mother a devout recusant, and her sonne a zealous protestant.</title>
            <author>Savage, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106433</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842149</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6779</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11532)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conference betvvixt a mother a devout recusant, and her sonne a zealous protestant seeking by humble and dutifull satisfaction to winne her vnto the trueth, and publike worship of god established nowe in England. Gathered by him whose hearts desire is, that all may come to the knowledge of God, and be saued.</title>
                  <title>Conference betwixt a mother a devout recusant, and her sonne a zealous protestant.</title>
                  <author>Savage, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 131, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legat, printer to the Vniversitie of Cambrige,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Francis Sauage.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A satisfaction for a devout recusant.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; trimmed at head, affecting running title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONFERENCE <hi>BET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IXT A</hi> MOTHER A DEVOVT RECVSANT, AND HER Sonne a zealous proteſtant, ſeeking by <hi>humble and dutifull ſatisfaction to</hi> winne her vnto the trueth, and <hi>publike worſhip of god eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> nowe in England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gathered by him whoſe hearts</hi> deſire is, that all may come to the <hi>knowledge of God, and</hi> be ſaued.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Corinth. 11.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Would to God you coulde a little tollerate my fooliſhneſſe, yea indeede beare with me. For I am zealous ouer you with a godly zeale.</p>
            </q>
            <p>PRINTED BY IOHN LEGAT, <hi>Printer to the Vniverſitie of Cambrige.</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>father in God, my</hi> VERY GOOD LORD GERVASE by the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, Lord</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Worceſter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat maketh me willing to publiſh this pamplet, your L. will eaſily iudge by the argument; what helpes I haue had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſo many as haue hard your Lorſhips publike exhortations or priuate conferences in matter of religion, will as eaſily coniecture, it being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede nothing els but a gleaning of your L. great harueſt, and a cluſter of your owne vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. And therefore what cauſe I haue to ſue for your honourable approbation, I neede not proclaime vnto the world, ſaue that I muſt needes confeſſe my ſelfe by many many bonds, more then I may well make knowne, to be ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all duty vnto your L. to whome next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der almightie God and her ſacred Maieſtie I owe whatſoeuer I haue beſides this corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man. I may not particularize your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and innumerable fauours, leaſt I exceede
<pb facs="tcp:6779:3"/>the limits of a preface, and breake the bonds of ſobrietie, and ſo incurre the iuſt diſpleaſure of your Lordſhip. Only I craue pardon herein to acknowledge that as once in the Vniuerſity by your Lordſhips happie hand I was brought into the ſheepfolde of the great ſheapheard, ſo in your honours ſeruice I haue beene led con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually by the ſame gratious hand in and out to the greene paſtures and pleaſant ſtreames of euer liuing water, and learned that which may ſtead me all my life long, and in the worlde to come for euer, it I be not wanting vnto my ſelfe. Wherefore may it pleaſe your Lordſhip, to vouchſafe me your wonted honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to couer whatſoeuer my defects in this attempt, and to accept this teſtimonie of my true and due affection to your L. I ſhall be ſtill more and more bounde, and I hope alwaies mindfull to bowe the knees of my heart vnto the higheſt, (whoſe recompence is a ſufficient reward) for the continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his gratious eye vpon you, and all your honourable affaires for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. humble chaplaine <hi>Francis Sauage.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Actantius for eloquence in the publiſhing of gods holy truth wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, <hi>Licèt veritas poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet ſine eloquentiâ defendi vt eſt à multis ſaepè defenſa, tamen cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate ac nitore ſermonis illuſtranda &amp; quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo diſſerenda eſt, vt potentius in animos influat.</hi> Wherein he ſeemeth ſomewhat to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all thoſe that want this skill, but by a little tranſpoſition we may keepe his meaning, and turne the ſentence thus. <hi>Although its meete with perſpicuitie and purity of ſpeech to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and ſet forth the trueth, and ſo, as it were,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 104</note> with skilfull hand to ſowe it, that it may more forcibly flowe into the mindes of men, yet may it be maintained well without eloquence and ornament of wordes:</hi> which is a ſufficient mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to all honeſt mindes which wiſh well to the proſperitie of Sion, to put to their helping hands though weake and feeble in the ſpirituall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods houſe. Yet a greater incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is that which S. Hierom ſaith, <hi>Fides pura non quaerit ſtrophas &amp; argumenta verborum. The purity of faith hunteth not after coulourable ſleightes and wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wordy arguments.</hi> But Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians ſpeech in ſome ſort enioyneth this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:6779:4"/>and exacteth it as a dutie. <hi>Veritas amat Spiritus ſancti figuram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ra Valent</note> 
               <hi>Orientem amat, nihil e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubeſcit, niſi ſolummodò abſcondi. The trueth loues the light, the morning ſtarre, &amp; breaking of the day, ſhee is abaſhed at nothing ſaue only the couer and night of darkenes and obſcurity.</hi> And ſure howe homely ſoeuer ſhee ſeeme in the eies of ſome, and in regard of the habite where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhee is ſome times attired, yet beeing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in her ſelfe like the kings daughter all glorious within, and in the eſtimate of the wiſe full of maieſtie and grace, and iuſtified euer of all her children, ſhee commeth forth like the Sunne riſing, as a bridegrome out of his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and as a giant readie to runne his courſe. Wherefore <hi>(gentle Reader)</hi> accept in good part, I pray thee, this my ſeruice and goodwill, woone by theſe inducements: and if this man of might meete thee in any corner of this ſimple cotage, looke not vpon the outward earthen walls, but caſt thine eie within vpon the prince himſelfe, yeelding thine homage of reuerence and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence euer due.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Fran. Sauage.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:4"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Auguſt. de Trin. lib. 1. cap. 2. &amp; 3.</bibl>
               <p>Nec pigebit me, ſicubi haeſito, quaerere, nec pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debit ſicubi erro, diſcere. Proinde quiſquis haec legit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vbi paritèr certus eſt pergat mecum: vbi paritèt haeſitat, quaerat mecum: vbi errorem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cogno ſcit, redeat adme: vbi meum, reuocet me. Ita ingreaiamur ſimul charitatis viam,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entes adeum, de quo dictum eſt, Quaerite facie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius ſemper.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6779:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6779:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A DIALOGVE</hi> BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IXT A Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and her ſonne being a <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the vniverſity &amp; come ouer into the</hi> country to ſee his friends, profitable to be <hi>be read of all that deſire to be ſatisfied</hi> touching matter of religion and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Church.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome Sonne, you ſhall goe with me to your fathers farme, this faire day is very fit to walke abroad, and moderate walking is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended of all as good phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I will gladly attend you Mother, both in regard of your pleaſure, and this fit oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for the exerciſe of our bodies, which is the beſt phiſicke that many a poore ſcholler
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6779:6"/>hath in the vniuerſity: but I hope the farme you goe vnto is not far off, becauſe you ſpeake of mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rate walking.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M</speaker>
               <p>What? knowe you not your fathers houſes? this is the good that cometh of your long abſence, &amp; your fathers care to ſend you ſo farre away, which hath much grieued me, and in which reſpect I haue often reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſend for you home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S</speaker>
               <p>Good Mother, I ſee and feele to my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> I haue euer done, your ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and bowels of louing kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wards me, and I muſt needes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my fathers great loue euen in this which you ſeeme to miſlike, that he ſent me to the vniuerſity, for ſure he did it in his ſpeciall care ouer me, and in wiſdome for my ſafety.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Safety? I pray you from what? would your mothers eye haue done you any harme?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I would be very loath, mother, to offend you, and therefore if I haue ſpoken any thing vnadviſedly, I humbly craue pardon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Nay ſonne, we haue not beene ſo long a ſunder, to fall out at firſt: and therefore I will not be offended ſo ſoone, but I will enioyne you to ſpeake plaine, and to tell me in earneſt what you meant by ſafety.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6779:6"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I beſeech you good mother, let me goe no further in this matter, my comming home to ſee you would doe me litle good if through my folly and vnapt ſpeech I ſhould procure your miſlike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you againe it ſhall not bee ſo, and therefore neither ſtand with me any longer, nor feare, but tell me your meaning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, vpon your kind promiſe of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, I confeſſe I meant ſafetie from miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in religion, whileſt I was young and eaſy to be led by thoſe whome I reuerenced.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Ah ſir: nowe you deale plainely with me indeede, and I ſee as plainely the fruites of your vniuerſity companie, and of your fathers care, euen to make a conceited young man of you, before you haue ripeneſſe of yeares to diſcerne in matters of ſuch weight, as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good mother, for mine vniuerſitie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie &amp; my fathers moſt louing care I bleſſe God, and thanke them both as I am bound: neither ſhall you by gods grace finde me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyted o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> head ſtrong aboue my true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: mine harty praier is for humility, and againſt pride.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne it is well ſaid, and ſo praying aſſure your ſelfe god will heare your requeſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6779:7"/>and grant your deſire: but yet for your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in diuinity I hope it is not ſo great, but that a poore woman that hath neithr Logicke nor Rhetorick, yet a little latine, may argue the caſe with you, and aske you of your newe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that I ſee hath gotten ſome fauour in your eies: howe you dare take liking of it, and reſt vpon it: ſince by all truely learned, it hath beene called and ſtill is reputed and helde for very feareful and damnable hereſie. Alas poore boy if thou ſhouldſt miſcarrie, thy father ſhould anſwer God for thee, and what a griefe it is to me, to thinke either of the one or the other, let my teares teſtifie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Deare mother, quiet your ſelfe, and thinke of neither: for by Gods grace there ſhall be no cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>No cauſe? when now being but a youth in compariſon, you are as full of hereſie as an egge is full of meate, and ſo like to taſt either euer or long of that liquour that firſt hath bene powred into you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>You are tolde it is hereſie, by thoſe that are not truely learned, as you tearme them, but ignorant, and ſo lead you and others awry with them: but god is able in his good time to let you ſee it is trueth and no hereſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>That ſhould be a great chaunge, ſonne,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6779:7"/>as I thinke, and becauſe I could as willingly heare you as any, and you ſeme to thinke the matter plain, I pray you let me heare what you can ſay, and what our new maſters haue taught you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Your firme and feruent loue to me, deare mother, giues me encouragement to ſpeake boldly vnto you what I am able &amp; yet within tearmes of duty and reuerence euer due vnto you: but if you will charge me to ſpeake any more, double againe vnto me your comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table promiſe of pardon in all things: for my hart trembleth for feare to offend you any waies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne, I doe double it, and aſſuredly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it, therefore be not afraid, your reſpectiue affection to me I note, &amp; it ſhall not hurt you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>My anſwere then good mother, as neere as either memory or my note booke, which I haue alſo about me will ſerue, ſhall be the verie wordes of ſuch worthy men as haue written on our ſide, that therby both the want of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie which is in my youth may be ſupplied with their credit, and the profit of reading our bookes which papiſts make ſo dangerous, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obſerued by as many as are not deſperatly ſicke of rebellion and contumacy againſt the Lord. Firſt therefore touching the name of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6779:8"/>hereſie,<note place="margin">Hereſie.</note> which euen now you mentioned, and I know you often heare out of their mouthes, who reſort vnto you: thus hath it beene an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered on our ſide many a time and often. As the accuſation is bitter and grievous, yea euen ſuch as the old father S. Ierome ſaith, <hi>No man ought to be patient no not in the ſuſpit o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eof:</hi> ſo is it not new or ſtraunge to haue gods truth ſlandered wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h this name: and therfore it is a good caueat, not to be carried away with the name, till we haue well examined the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and found it to agree with the name, and rightly to be ſo called: which that we may do, we muſt knowe, that for iuſt proofe of hereſie, two things are necceſſarily required: firſt that it be an Errour in matter of Chriſtian faith: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that it be ſtoutly and obſtinatly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: otherwiſe, an errour in Gods truth without obſtinate maintenance is not an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. S. Auſten ſaith therefore, <hi>Errare poſſum, haereticus eſſe non poſſum; In an errour I may be, but an heretique I cannot be:</hi> meaning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he intended not obſtinately to maintaine an errour. Whervnto is agreeable that good ſaying of S. Hilary, <hi>Illis in eo quod neſciunt poteſt adhuc in tuto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe ſalus ſicredant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lar. de Trin. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>tibi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò iam omnia ad ſalutem clauſa ſunt qui negas quod iam ignorare non potes: They for as much
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6779:8"/>as they knovve not the truth, may haue their ſalvation in fafety, if aftervvard they beleeue, but all hope of health is ſhut vp from thee, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thou denieſt that thing vvhich thou canſt not chooſe but knowe.</hi> See, howe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous wilfull and obſtinate maintenance of an error is, but neither of theſe two points will be found in vs, and therefore farre are wee from iuſtly deſeruing the name of heretiques, or our true faith the name of hereſie. This is an olde practiſe of Satan to deale thus with Gods trueth and the profeſſours thereof. S. Paul was called before the iudges to make anſwer to a matter of hereſie, as you may read to your great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment in the Acts of the Apoſtles and he anſwered,<note place="margin">Act. 24.</note> that indeede according to that way which they called hereſie, he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the God of his fathers. But for all their calling and bawling it was far from beeing ſo, becauſe he beleeued all things which were written in the law &amp; the Prophets, and for that his manner of worſhippe was wholly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the ſcriptures, which no hereſie can be. Chriſt our deare Sauiour for no other cauſe was called a Samaritane, but onely for that he was thought to haue fallen to a certaine newe religion, and to be the author of a new ſect.<note place="margin">in Apologe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Tertullian witneſſeth that in his time euen
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6779:9"/>this very religion which wee now profeſſe, was called a ſect and hereſie, that thereby Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces eares might be ſtopped from hearing any thing ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or written in defence of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Euſebius doth the like,<note place="margin">4. c. 18.</note> ſaying, that the religion of Chriſt was called, <hi>impiorum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian orum Haereſis, The hereſie of the wicked Chriſtians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad. Tit.</note> S. Hierome conſidering well the place before named in the Acts, ſaieth, <hi>Quod magis mirum ſit, &amp;c.</hi> And that wee may the more maruaile we may once againe read this place of the Acts of the Apoſtles; where wee finde that the Chriſtian and Eccleſiaſtical diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline was euen then of wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Many others haue witneſſed as much; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efore ſince it is no new thing, but the very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of Satan euer, I truſt you ſee there is great cauſe not to be carried away with mens ſpeaches, whoſe eies be blinded by the god of this worlde, but with true and ſound proofes. If they cannot ſhew that we haue fallen away from Chriſt, nor from his Apoſtles, nor from the prophets, if we beleeue (as ſurely we doe) all that is written in them, &amp; maintain nothing as neceſſarie to ſalvation, but what may be plainely ſhewed to be taught vs by them, how iniurious and ſhamfull yea fearefull a dealing it is neuertheleſſe to call vs Heretiques, good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6779:9"/>mother conſider in your ſelfe. Me thinkes in this place S. Auſtens ſpeech ſomtimes to Petili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an the Donatiſt, is good, who ſaid thus:<note place="margin">contra Petil. 2. cap. 85.</note> 
                  <hi>Vtrum nos ſchiſmatici ſumus an vos, nec ego, nec tu, ſed Chriſtus interrogetur, vt indicet Eccleſiam ſuam: Whether of vs be ſciſmatiques (or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques (aske not of either of vs, but let Chriſt be asked for vs both, that he may ſhewe vs his owne Church:</hi> that is, let the ſcriptures bee ſearched and let them declare the trueth, which they will doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne, for your firſt point, that it is not ſafe to iudge of things by names, becauſe Gods truth hath bin called hereſy as you haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I ſee it plainely, I ioyne with you, and take it for a good caveat hereafter to beware: but for your ſecond point, that therefore you ſhould not be counted heretiques, becauſe you ſay you holde nothing diſagreeable to the ſcriprures, I cannot approoue it, becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques as I haue heard, at al times haue boaſted of ſcripture as you doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good mother, I am very glad you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue how truth hath bene ſlandered with the name of hereſie,<note place="margin">Scripture.</note> and therefore how fit it is in matters of ſalvation not to be mooued by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of men, but euer to ſearch &amp; ſeeke for due &amp; true proofe: and for the ſecond point, I truſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6779:10"/>God ſhall make you ſee it alſo, if it pleaſe you to goe along with me. True it is which you ſay you haue heard, that heretiques alleadge ſcripture, and you knowe that the diuell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe who is as bad as any heretique,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</note> alleadged ſcriptures: but what then? is not it therfore a ſafe way to cleaue to the ſcriptures, and only vpon them to ground our faith? yes ſurely: which ſhall appeare euen by this practiſe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan being duly conſidered; for ſuch is the skill of that old ſubtill ſerpent, that as he knoweth to fitte his temptations to the humour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of them whome he tempteth, ſo he vſeth to ſet vpon men by thoſe perſwaſions which he is moſt likely to ſeduce them by, as to Eve in paradice he promiſed the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>od. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chron. 18.11.</note> to obſtinate Pharaoh he preſented lying wonders: to wicked Ahab delighting in lies he came in the month and conſent of many falſe prophets: to the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and hypocriticall Iewes he pretended the temple of the Lord:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. 7.4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 19.27. &amp; 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to the populous &amp; ancient heathen vniuerſalitie and antiquity: &amp; to our Sauiour the written word of God, which he thought (if any thing) would preuaile with him. So the diuell in alleadging onely ſcripture againſt our Sauiour turneth himſelfe into an angell of light, and would ſeeme to doe that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6779:10"/>which is moſt holy in it ſelfe, moſt acceptable vnto god, moſt comfortable to men, moſt ſure for their ſafegard and protection; which doth not di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>credit the triall of truth in points of faith by ſcripture only, but rather countenance and confirme it, becauſe it argueth the diſpoſition and ſetled affection of our bleſſed Sauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards theſe ſacred writings, that he made them the tower of his defence, the rocke of his ſafegarde, the foundation of his whole obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; accounted nothing a ground of faith and dutie but onely ſcripture, and therefore that we likewiſe ſhould cleaue faſt to the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God, turning neither to the right nor left hand, but walking conſtantly in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience thereof. Wherefore though this alleadging of ſcripture be a worke of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, both becauſe he did miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alleadge it, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out a principall part of the ſentence, and ſo corrupting it, and alſo for that he did it as a lying ſpirit to deceiue. Yet to alledge the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture rightly, with an vpright minde to a good ende, ſhall euer be as the dutie of Gods people, ſo the ſhield and buckler of their defence, yea the crowne and glorie of the children of light, whereby they ſhall reſemble their head our bleſſed Saviour Chriſt Ieſus, who as you may ſee in the goſpel gaue not ouer his holde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6779:11"/>the deuill abuſed it, but with ſcripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he anſwered him, and ſo both iuſtified himſelfe, and confounded his aduerſary, which alſo hath beene the manner, good mother, of the church of God at all times. As namely at the firſt moſt holy and vncorrupt Councell helde at Hieruſalem by the Apoſtles themſelues,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 15.</note> where the queſtion debated was whether the beleeuing Gentiles could be ſaued onely by faith in Chriſt Ieſus without circumciſion and the obſeruation of the lawe of Moſes, as Paul and Barnabas affirmed and preached againſt certaine who came from Iudea, and taught the contrary. For the deciding whereof, in that moſt catholike and orthodoxall Councel S. Peter alleadged the teſtimony of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe who ſent him to the Gentiles (Cornelius and his friendes) to preach vnto them, not the lawe of Moſes, but the word of the goſpel, that they might beleeue, and bleſſed his miniſterie with happy ſucceſſe, giuing vnto them the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, and purifying their hearts by ſaith, which he calleth Gods teſtimony. God (ſaith he) bare witneſſe vnto them giuing them the holy ghoſt &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>And S. Iames in his ſentence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged the written word of God both to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that which S. Peter had deliuered, and to ende the controuerſie:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 14.</note> Symeon (ſaith he) hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6779:11"/>declared howe god firſt viſited the Gentiles, &amp; tooke of them a people vnto his name, and to this agree the wordes of the Prophets, as it is written &amp;c. Likewiſe at the famous Counſell of Nice, the worthy Emperour Conſtantine whome god raiſed vp to ende the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Church, and to giue it reſt, ſaide thus to the biſhops aſſembled there.<note place="margin">Theod. lib. 1. cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae &amp; Apoſtolicae literae, &amp;c.</hi> the writings of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles and the ſayings of the olds Prophets doe clearely inſtruct vs, what iudgement we ought to haue of the meaning and will of God. Therefore laying aſide all contention let vs ſeeke out of thoſe heauenly oracles the aſſoiling of our queſtions. And of the Arrian herericks, who in that counſel were ouerthrown, another ſaith thus, <hi>Explicantes ſacras ſcripturas ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s euertimus,<note place="margin">Socr. l. 1. c. 6.</note> by opening and expounding the holy ſcriptures we overthrowe them.</hi> The like rule was follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the counſell helde at Conſtantinople, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the hereticke Macedonius, that denied the divinitie of the holy ghoſt: neuer mooue queſtion hereof, ſaith Athanaſius,<note place="margin">ad Serapion.</note> but learne of the holy ſcriptures, for the onely proofes that you ſhall there finde are ſufficient. And in another place the ſame father ſaith, <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ſufficiunt adveritatis inſtructionem ſiue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6779:12"/>institutionem:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ra Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l Idola.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſcriptures are ſufficient to inſtruct vs in the trueth:</hi> Marke I pray you the word <hi>Sufficiunt.</hi> In the other two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels alſo of Epheſus and Chalcedon,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vagrius.</note> we read of the ſame courſe: all things were concluded by the wordes of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles. The auncient father Origen ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. lib. 10.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnde quàm propè periculis illi ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> See and conſider in what daunger they be, that haue no care to read the holy ſcriptures, for by the ſame ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures onely the iudgement of this triall muſt be allowed.<note place="margin">ierom. hom. 1.</note> And in another place, <hi>Neceſſe eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſcripturas ſanctas in teſtimonium vocare, ſenſus quippe noſtri &amp; enarrationes ſine iis teſtibus non habent fidem. VVe muſt needes call to witneſſe the holy ſcriptures, for our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and expoſitions without thoſe witneſſes carry no credit:</hi> a notable ſaying if it pleaſe you to marke it. And with him S. Auſten fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth, when he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; Grat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Solis Canonicis ſciptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſine vlla recuſatione conſenſum debeo. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Canonicall ſcriptures do I owe my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent without gainſaying.</hi> The ſame father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, when he diſputed againſt Petilian the Donatiſt,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c Vnit. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leſ. c. 3.</note> ſaid, <hi>Let not theſe vvordes be heard betweene vs I ſay, or you ſay, but let vs rather ſpeake in this wiſe, thus ſaith the Lord. Aufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur de medio chartae noſtrae, procedat in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6779:12"/>codex dei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">contra li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l. 3 c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Away with our bookes and let Gods booke come in place. Siue enim de Chriſto, ſiue de Eccleſia ſiue de quacun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliâre, quae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet adfidem vitam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſtram, non dicamſi nos, &amp;c. For whether it be of Chriſt, or of his Church or of any thing els what ſoeuer pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning either to our life or to our faith, I will not ſay if I my ſelfe, but if an angel from heauen ſhall teach vs otherwiſe then we haue receiued in the bookes of the law and in the goſpel, holde him accurſed.</hi> This is the proofe (ſaith he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine) <hi>quae nec falli, nec fallere poteſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">de peccat. m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; remiſt. l. 1. c. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>which can neither deceiue, nor be deceiued.</hi> To the verie ſame effect ſpeake all the fathers I aſſure you, if it were needfull to repeat their wordes. <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you</hi> (ſaith S Chriſoſtom) <hi>weigh not what this man or that thinketh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in 2. Cor. ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>but touching all things ſearch the ſcriptures.</hi> S. Hierom ſaith, <hi>Quod de ſcripturis autoritatem non habet, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acilitate contemnitur qua probatur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in 23. Mat.</note> 
                  <hi>that which is not warranted by the ſcriptures, may as eaſily be contemned as alleadged.</hi> And ſo the reſt of the fathers particularly euery one: and therefore (good Mother) weigh it and note it, that albeit both heretiques &amp; deuills abuſe the ſcriptures by alleadging them to euill endes, yet is it the true way and the onely way to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued by, and to finde reſt for our conſciences
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6779:13"/>in all matter of controuerſie, touching either faith or manners, ſo taken, ſo taught, ſo held by Chriſt, by his Apoſtles, and by all the godly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and worthy approoued Councels in the world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe that if the ſcriptures bee rightly applyed, they are indeede the ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that ought to be ſtood vpon; but howe ſhall that appeare, that you apply them rightly, more then thoſe whome you acknowledge heretiques, which likewiſe haue alleadged them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good mother, giue me leaue to make make much of that which I gaine from you in this conference, and to recken it vp as deere vnto my verie ſoule, for the duty I owe you, and for the deſire I haue, that the trueth may be revealed vnto you. This therefore now you ſee and confeſſe, that although all the hereticks in the world, and all the diuels in hell ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſcripture, and abuſe it, yet hath it not bin giuen of God in vaine, but ſerueth as a ſure ground of our faith and actions, euery thing beeing alowable that is conſonant vnto it, and that alwaies faultie, which is contrarie vnto it: and therefore that we ought not to be beaten from it, by any deuiſe of Satan, but ſtedfaſtly to ſtick vnto it, and euer to depend vpon it, as the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6779:13"/>only ſure ancher of our ſoules, in like manner as all thoſe worthy men and Councels before mentioned haue done. <hi>For what quietnes to my minde like to this? Thou Lord haſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me thus to beleeue and thus to doe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſo beleeve and ſo doe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Interpretatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of ſcripture.</note> Only you ſticke nowe at the right application of them, and aske howe ſhall you know that? Surely mother, you ſhall know it euen to your full contentment if you will doe as others before you godly and holy perſons both men &amp; women haue done.<note place="margin">lib. 83. quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Saint Auſten ſaith, <hi>Solet circumſtantia Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum illuminare ſententiam, The circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſcriptures is vvout to giue light and open the meaning thereof.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in Eſai. c. 19</note> Saint Hierome ſaith, <hi>Moris eſt ſcripturarum obſcuris manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta ſubnectere, Its the manner of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures after harde thinges to ioyne other things that be plaine.</hi> Tertullian ſaith, <hi>Opertet ſecundum plura intelligi pauciora, The fewer things muſt be expounded by the moe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hil. de Trin. 9.</note> S. Hilary ſaith, <hi>Intelligentia dictorum ex cauſa dicendi fumenda eſt, the vnderſtanding of things ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe of ſpeaking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, expraepoſitis &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus, by things going before and following after.</hi> S, Cyril ſaith,<note place="margin">Cyr. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c. 2.</note> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we woulde vnderſtande any place of ſcripture, we muſt conſider three things, the time
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6779:14"/>when it was written; the perſon that writ, and to whome, or of whom, and the matter it ſelfe. Many ſuch good rules haue the fathers which as you ſee, greatly help in the thing you deſire, and which if we vſe, no doubt we ſhall finde as they found: then haue we the gratious promiſe of gods holy ſpirit if we aske it; and what a ſure guide is that? the performance of which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſee in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">c. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>then opened he their vnderſtanding that they might vnderſtand the ſcriptures.</hi> See it in that good woman Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia the purple ſeller,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 16.</note> whoſe heart was alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened. This bleſſed gift doth the Apoſtle think of, when he wiſheth to the Epheſians the ſpirit of wiſdome and revelation that the eyes of their vnderſtanding might be opened,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſ. 1.17.</note> &amp; light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that they might knowe, &amp;c. So to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians and to the Coloſsians; and of this ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Elihu in the booke of Iob,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lip. 1.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>loſt. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in man but the inſpiration of the almighty giueth vnderſtanding.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 32.8.</note> This did king Dauid knowe, and therefore asked this heauenly gift by earneſt prayer, often ſaying, <hi>Teach me O Lord, teach me thy statutes, teach me thy waies, open mine eyes that I may beholde the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things in thy lawe.</hi> Origen ſaith, <hi>Orandus eſt Deus vt aperiat librum obſignatum, we muſt beſeech God by prayer to open the booke that is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6779:14"/>ſealed</hi> The Lord is no reſpect of perſons, but as he hath done, he will doe, and heare the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of his children that wiſh to know his will. This is the way, mother, this is the way that neuer failed any who vſed it, neither will it faile you. But you ſhall ſee by it the true and right applying of the ſcriptures, howſoeuer others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and miſ-conſtrue them. In a worde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore marke I beſeech you, that we doe not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme all caſes of doubt to be by manifeſt and open wordes plainely expreſſed in ſcripture, for ſo there ſhould neede no expoſition, but we ſay and affirme that there is no caſe in religion neceſſarie to Gods worſhip or mans ſalvation ſo darke and doubtful, but it may neceſſarily be either prooued or diſprooued by true collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conference in ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M</speaker>
               <p>Sonne, I marke your ſpeech well and your words fall not to the ground, yet I hope you will confeſſe that our men doe well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the doctours as they doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Surely mother, I doe confeſſe the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours of the Church worthy of more regard then is giuen them ſometimes by Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes.<note place="margin">Doctoures.</note> And you ſee by my alleadging of them that I greatly regard them. But ſeeing you haue mentioned this matter I doe hartely intreat you to marke a fewe things in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6779:15"/>Firſt that they are not <hi>Domini ſedduces noſtri, Not our Lords but our leaders.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. Auguſtin ſaith, <hi>Other writers or fathers (beſides the holy ſcriptures) I read in this ſort, that be their learning or holineſſe neuer ſo great, I wil not thinke it true becauſe they haue thought ſo, but becauſe they are able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me ſo either by Canonicall writers, or els by ſome likely reaſon.</hi> Likewiſe againe, This kind of writings (meaning the holy doctoures) muſt be reade not with neceſsitie to beleeue each thing, but with libertie to iudge each thing. For we may not conſent to the biſhops, notwithſtanding they be Catholike,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nit. Eccl. c.</note> if they iudge contrarie to the holy Canonicall ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. This is the right credit of holy fathers; they are not the trueth of God it ſelfe, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly witneſſes vnto the trueth: no more haue they they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues euer deſired, no leſſe ought we euer to giue them. Heare I pray you the words of the ſame father againe, we receiue not the diſputations or writings of any men be they neuer ſo Catholicke or praiſe-worthy,<note place="margin">Fortunat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. 111.</note> as we receiue the Canonicall ſcriptures, but that ſauing their reuerence we may well reprooue or refuſe ſome things in their writings, if it hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen we finde they haue otherwiſe though then the trueth may beare them out: ſuch am I in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6779:15"/>the writings of others, and ſuch would I wiſh others to be in mine. He writeth to S. Hierom againe to the ſame effect <hi>Non puto frater,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ep. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. My brother I doe not thinke you would haue vs ſo to read your bookes as if they were written by the Apoſtles and Prophets.</hi> To the like purpoſe writeth Tertullian of himſelfe and the reſt, wherein their holy modeſtie is worthy great praiſe for euer, they tooke not vpon them to be Lords but leaders: and to that ende the Lord hath giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as excellent lights to his church. So of Counſels S. Auſten telleth vs, <hi>that the former are reiected by the later, &amp;c.</hi> Likewiſe Panormitan ſaith, <hi>vve ought to giue more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to on lay man, then to an whole councell and to the Pope, if he bring better authority and more reaſon.</hi> This is my firſt obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this matter of the doctours. My ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is this which I humbly pray you to marke, that as ſcriptures haue beene abuſed by heretiques, ſo haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and therefore if we muſt giue ouer the one for miſ-applyings, ſo muſt we the other al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ſame reaſon. The Arrian here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques alleadged Origens bookes for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and ſafegard:<note place="margin">Socr. l. 4. c. Concil. Ch act. 2. p. 732</note> the heretique Eutiches ſaide, I haue read the writings of the father Saint Cyprian, as alſo of other holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and of the holy father Saint Athanaſius.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6779:16"/>Another of his ſect cryed, this is my faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the expoſition of 318 fathers. The Neſtorian heretiques alleadged the Counſel of Nice:<note place="margin">p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> and not to weary you with many, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſcorus the heretique cried out in the open Councell of Chalcedon,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1. p. 767.</note> 
                  <hi>Ego habeo teſtimonia ſanctorum patrum, I haue the teſtimonies of the holy fathers,</hi> Athanaſius, Gregory, Cyrill, I varie not from them in any point: I am thrown forth and baniſhed with the fathers, I defend the fathers doctrine, I haue their iudgement vttered not by chaunce or vnaduiſedly, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining expreſſed in their bookes. Therefore you ſee, good mother, that heretiques haue cried as well fathers, fathers as ſcriptures, ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and yet neither the one nor the other for this cauſe to be reiected. My third obſeruation might be of counterfeit and young yeſterday fathers alleadged by papiſts, and of ſmall credit or reuerence giuen to fathers by them that boaſt thus of fathers when they pleaſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I aſſure you we haue notable examples, with many things moe, but that I feare to be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yet ſonne, ſeeing our faith was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yours, me thinks the fathers ſhould rather make for vs then for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>And why ſay you not ſo of the ſcriptures
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6779:16"/>which were many yeares before any of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Surely if your faith were before ours,<note place="margin">Old faith.</note> as well ſcriptures as fathers would giue on your ſide, and indeed both would make for you,<note place="margin">New faith.</note> the fathers deſiring to holde nothing but that they iudged agreeable to ſcripture, which euer they make the rule and ground of faith and trueth, and not their own writings, as you haue ſeene. But good Mother they abuſe you and many moe, that tell you your faith (that is, as nowe you meane, the Romiſh faith) was before ours: for I aſſure you it is not ſo, but very newe and younge in compariſon of ours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What? our faith newe, Sonne, &amp; yours old? Alas I ſee theſe newe teachers haue poſſeſt you mightily, &amp; you are ſo carried away with them, that they are able to make you beleeue any thing. Why tell me the crowe is white or the ſnowe is blacke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good Mother, the Lord hath mooued your heart to heare me ſpeake who am yours and of you. If I ſpeake amiſſe, as you thinke, and ſo as you cannot conſent vnto me &amp; with me, leaue we it both to the working power of a mighty God, who in further time can giue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light and vnderſtanding to his children that humbly craue it, and are not lifted vp with an high hand to withſtand his offered grace.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6779:17"/>Onely according to this motherly loue that you haue began to ſhew me, vouchſafe to here me ſtill, vpon what groundes I haue ſetled my ſelfe, and with what proofe I am mooued to thinke as I doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſonne, I coulde not abide or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to heare any other once ſpeake of ſuch a ſtraunge thing as this, but ſay you on what you liſt, you are my childe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I doe verely beleeue it ſeemeth moſt ſtraunge to you and to many moe of your ſide, to heare that your religion is newe and ours olde. Yet I doubt not but to make it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently apparent vnto you and all whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall without preiudice duly conſider my allegations and proofe. But firſt I muſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret my ſelfe in a worde or two what I meane by your faith and religion. I pray you therefore when I ſpeake of your Romiſh reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion thinke not that I meane the whole do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and all the articles of faith and religion taught and profeſſed by the Papiſts, but onely thoſe points of doctrine wherein they differ from vs. For in generall they hold the doctrine of the lawe and tenne commandements as we doe, ſauing that they leaue out the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement which forbiddeth the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Idols and Images, making two of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6779:17"/>tenth: they profeſſe alſo the ſumme of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, at leaſt in generalitie and in wordes, to wit, <hi>that Chriſt Ieſus perfect God and perfect man hath wrought our full redemption, and by the blood of his croſſe and pretious death, &amp; prrfect obedience hath deliuered vs from eternall death, the fierch and euerlaſting wrath of God, the due deſert of our tranſgreſsions, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for vs euerlaſting peace and bliſſe:</hi> they maintaine alſo and profeſſe in wordes as we alſo doe the three creedes, the Nicene, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſian, and the Apoſtolike creede, wherein is compriſed the ſumme of our faith and the doctrine we profeſſe, they acknowledge that moſt excellent forme and paterne of prayer taught vs in the goſpel by our Sauiour, and vſe it, and many other good and godly prayers which we alſo vſe, euen all thoſe vvelneere in our common liturgie except a very fevve for our moſt gratious Queene &amp;. ſauing that they vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in latin, vve in engliſh that all may vnderſtand and ſay amen. Wherefore vvhen I ſay that your religion is nevv, meane not ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerally, nor of the things before rehearſed, but only in reſpect of certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other articles and points of religion maintained by Romiſh catholikes, as namely, 1. that the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the church are of equall authority vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h the vvorde of god
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6779:18"/>to be embraced with like reuerence and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 2. that the vulgar latin tranſlation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Hieromes is onely authenticall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. that the imputation of Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and obedience to the faithfull is a fantaſie without ground in Gods word. 4. that the bread in the ſacrament of the Euchariſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated into the body of Chriſt is to be adored. 5. that the faithfull are able to keepe the whole lawe of God. 6. that the Pope is Chriſts generall vicar vpon earth, hauing abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power to ratifie or diſanull all manner of decrees and ordinances, and to diſpenſe with the expreſſe and moral precepts of God at his pleaſure. 7. That the whole Church without him can neither enact nor infringe any lawe eccleſiaſticall, nor interpret any ſcripture. 8. that the holy ſcriptures ought not to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into any vulgar tongue or reade of the lay people. 9. that the ſacrament of the Lords ſupper is to be adminiſtred onely in bread and not in wine,<note place="margin">Quia ſapor poſsit genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſuſpitionem quòd eſſet ibi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inum.</note> leaſt as the Sorboniſts at Paris ſay, the people ſhould ſmell it to be wine and ſo doubt of tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 10. that good works are meritorious, and that by them we are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the ſight of God. 11. that the ſoules of the faithfull dying before perfect repentance, ſuffer the torments of purgatory. 12. that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6779:18"/>are to be made in an vnknowen tongue, &amp; ſuch like: of al which and the reſt, wherein they diſagree from vs, I ſay they are newe and ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday opinions in compariſon of the faith which we hold conſonant to the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and thoſe famous ancient creeds before mentioned. And therefore now to proceede to the declaration of that which I haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken touching the noueltie of your faith. Thus good Mother, haue our men written &amp; at this day teach: that it goeth not with Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it doth with the ſtatutes of the realme, &amp; iudgements at common law, where the later is thought to be the better: but in religion the firſt and eldeſt is beſt. Therefore they euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that golden ſaying of Tertullian, that is true which was firſt, that is firſt, which was from the beginning, and that was from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning which was deliuered by the Apoſtles, but our faith is that was deliuered by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles yours is not, therfore ours is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſo firſt, yours not, and therefore later. Now that ours is that which was deliuered by the Apoſtles they prooue it thus. Another an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient father ſaith, That which the Apoſtles preached and deliuered to the world by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,<note place="margin">Irenaeus.</note> they afterward by the will of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to writing, that for euer it might be the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6779:19"/>foundation and ground of faith. Wherevpon it followeth, that which the Apoſtles preached is the old, auncient, Catholike and Apoſtolike ſaith, but that which they haue written is that which they preached: ſo ſaith this father; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which is written is the true auncient Catholike, and Apoſtolike faith, &amp; that is ours. For, as I haue ſaide, we hold nothing as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to ſalvation but that which is truly taught vs out of theſe written ſcriptures. Therefore our faith is that which was deliuered by the Apoſtles, your faith is not that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. For your men wil not be tried by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures onely, as knowing that many things they hold haue no warrant there, but haue deuiſed vnwritten traditions, therefore yours is not that which was deliueeed by the Apoſtles, and not the old faith, but a late newe faith deviſed by men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M</speaker>
               <p>VVhy? that which was deliuered by tradition,<note place="margin">Tradition.</note> was deliuered by the Apoſtles as wel as that which they wrot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>True Mother, if it could as ſoundly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vnto vs what they deliuered, as it doth by their writings what they preached But this father that I named vnto you, ſaith, they wrot that which they deliuered, and they wrote it by the will of God as not truſting tradition vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6779:19"/>and they wrote it to be for euer the ground of our faith, noting that vnwritten tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition may not be the ground, becauſe it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and full of imperfection as I could ſhewe you, if we were to ſpeake of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Therefore ſeeing this which is written is certainly and aſſuredly that which they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and we hold nothing but that which is agreeable to this, which is written, you ſee it is moſt plaine, that we holde nothing but that which the Apoſtles themſelues deliuered, and ſo our faith the old faith which was from the beginning and firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely if you holde nothing but that which is written, it is certaine that that which was written was deliuered by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and ſo it followeth that you hold no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that which was deliuered by the Apoſtles and Prophets, and therfore your faith olde indeede and not to be reiected. And for tradition, although we may be told that this and that was deliuered by the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours, and ſo by them to theirs againe to this day, yet I muſt needes confeſſe that is not ſo manifeſt and plaine as which is written, neither doth it yeeld ſuch content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to my conſcience. But I can not tell what to ſay it is a ſure and ſteadfaſt way to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6779:20"/>truſt to that which is written, rather then to that which is reported, and yet I am loath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o offend, you ſhal giue me leaue to pauſe &amp; think more of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea deere Mother, and with the hart of a dutifull child I ſay the father of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt lighten the eyes of your vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all things to the glory of his great name and your eternall comfort: but be you aſſured in this that we hold nothing as needfull to our ſaluation, but that which is written in expreſſe wordes, or by ſure and plaine collection, and therefore make the conſequence as the Lord ſhall direct you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Howe then commeth it to paſſe that your religion is ſtill called new, new?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Even as I told you before, it is one of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans trickes to diſcredit trueth, and hath in all times beene vſed of him. But as then your ſelfe collected by that which I alleadged, that it is not ſafe to be lead by tearmes and names with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due conſidering howe iuſtly and truely they are giuen, ſo I beſeech you do here again, and be not mooued with the name: for queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onles there can nothing be more ſpitefully ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt the religion of God, then to accuſe it of noueltie, as a matter lately found out. For as there can be no change in God himſelfe, ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6779:20"/>ought there be no change in his religion Yet ſtill I ſay, Satan hath taken this courſe euen from the beginning to call trueth newe, which indeede is not onely of greateſt antiquitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting. That vngratious &amp; blood thirſtie Haman, when he ſought to procure the king Aſſuerus his dſpleaſure againſt the Iewes, vſed this ſlaunder againſt them of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veltie, telling the king that he had in his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a kinde of people that vſed certaine newe lawes of their own &amp;c.<note place="margin">Act. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paul alſo began firſt to preach and expound the Goſpel at Athens, he was called a tidings-bringer of new Gods, that is, of a newe religion: for ſaid the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians, <hi>may we not knowe of thee what newe doctrine this is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Origen again telleth vs of Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that when he wrot of ſet purpofe againſt Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the ende he might ſcornefully ſcoſſe at the goſpell, he accuſed it of noueltie and ſaid:<note place="margin">Orig. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lſum.</note> 
                  <hi>vvhat hath God after ſo many ages now at laſt bethought himſelfe?</hi> whoſe vile blaſphemies that auncient father in his bookes written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him anſwereth. Euſebius alſo ſaith, that the Chriſtian religion from the beginnnig for verie ſpite was called new and ſtraunge,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c. 4.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sentence was giuen of condemnation that S. Audrewe ſhould be crucified for teaching and enterpriſing a newe ſect and taking away
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6779:21"/>the religion of their Gods. Shall we then bee mooued with this tearme, and carried away with this name? No, God forbid. Theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are a faire warning for vs to take heede of that lightneſſe and raſhneſſe. Let the deuil rage againſt trueth with what names God ſhall ſuffer him, and his members, yet this ſhall euer ſtand, that the doctrine of the Church is elder then any Idolatrie or ſuperſtition of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that the doctrine of the Goſpell was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in Paradiſe by God himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>The ſeede of the vvoman ſhall bruiſe the ſerpent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> head.</hi> That the writings of Moſes are elder the any writings of the Gentiles, the doctrine of the Apoſtles elder then Popery or any other hereſie, and that we at this day hold nothing, as I haue often ſaid, but what appeareth out of the Apoſtles owne writings alowed both by vs and our aduerſaries to be their vvritinges, to be their ovvne doctrine deliuered to the Church to be beleeued, and for men and vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be ſaued by.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely I ſee ſtill it is not ſafe to be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away vvith names, and to beleeue all to be nevve, vvhich is called ſo, or all olde vvhich is named olde: for ſo vve may be deceiued. But yet in ſhevve of the vvorlde ours hath had a longer continuance then yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6779:21"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt needes here once againe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you what I meane by your religion, to wit thoſe pointes of doctrine onely wherein you differ from vs. And then I anſwer, firſt that your religion euen in ſhewe of the world hath not had a longer continuance then ours, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the principall points whereon wee ſtand, as namely, 1. the articles of our Creede which is a briefe and ſumme of catholik faith, as Athanaſius plainely witneſſeth,<note place="margin">Symbol Athanaſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Haee eſt fides Catholica,</hi> and the Councell of Trent confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. 1. the acknowledgment of gods diuine law, and the worſhipping of god according to that law. 3. the doctrine of repentance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dead workes and of faith in Ieſus Chriſt for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinne. 4 the doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper, which are the fundamentall points of out faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the rocke whereon we build our ſoules and Church, and without controuerſie of greater antiquity then thoſe points of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which we call popery. Beſides I anſwer, although your religion in ſhew of the world, were more ancient then ours, yet that ought to be no diſparagement to ours, or adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to yours: for god afflicteth his church as pleaſeth him, &amp; maketh vs ſee that it is like the moone whervnto it is compared, now growing, now
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6779:22"/>ful, now waining, we may not meſure truth by worldly cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but by that rule which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faileth, the word of God, and if our faith be that which there is taught &amp; warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, the you haue heard which is the old true Catholik faith indeed and therfore to be receiued, helde and defended, though for a thouſand yeares the Lord hath made it a ſtraunger in this or that place to puniſh thereby the ſinnes of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or countrie. <hi>Vetus conſuetudo non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicat veritate, Olde cuſtome doth not preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the truth:</hi> ſaith good S. Auſten, <hi>Nec dici debet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ug. De Ciuit. l. 10. c. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>quare modò? quare ſero? quoniam mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis conſilium non eſt humauo ingenio peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trabile: Neither may we ſay, why commeth it now?</hi> (Good Mother marke it) <hi>why commeth it ſo late? for the councell of God that ſent it is vnſearchable to the wiſdome of man.</hi> Thus ſpeake the Papiſts in theſe daies: where was your religion before Luther? where hath it beene this many hundred yeares? had God no Church till now? &amp;c. But S. Auſten telleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſpeake not well, they ought not to ſay ſo: for Gods councell is known to himſelfe, and we cannot reach vnto it. <hi>Religionis autoritas non est tempore estimanaa ſed numine, nec quo die, ſedquid colere caeperis iutueri convenit: quodenim verum eſt, ſerum non eſt. The au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6779:22"/>of religion muſt be weighed by god not by time, &amp; we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider not vpon what day, but vvhat thing we began to worſhip, the thing that is true is neuer to late.</hi> The Ieſuits tell vs wonders of their conuerting the Indians and other people to the Romiſh faith, and woulde they like that thoſe nations ſhould ſay where hath this religion beene all this while? woulde they not ſay as Arnobius ſaith, <hi>that which is true ſhould euer be vvelcome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arnob. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>howe long ſoeuer the time of darkeneſſe hath beene?</hi> Why doe they then teach any to ſtand vpon ſuch queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Goſpel nowe preached? Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>If I ſpeake the trueth vvhy doe you not beleeue me?</hi> and that is the good iſſue indeede to conſider the matter whether it bee true or no: which is euer found by the weight of the ſanctuary, the word of God. Certenly we teach no falſe religion but offer the trueth for iſſue, praying that if it be found true by the touchstone mentioned, it may be entertained, and ſo much the more hartely, by how much ſhee hath beene long from home. For ſo wee deale with our friendes, and doe not vtterly denie them if they haue beene long away. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenly we haue planted no newe religion, but renewed the olde (I meane in reſpect of certen pointes corrupted by your men) that was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6779:23"/>founded and vſed by the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and other holy fathers in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, &amp; of this long late time by meane of the multitude of Romiſh traditions and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities hath beene drowned with traditions &amp; fantaſies though painted with colour of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and continuance, yet are new, vaine, and naught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot deny ſonne, but it is true that you ſay, there may be <hi>vetuſtas erroris, an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of error</hi> (for you know I haue ſome latin, not yet forgotten) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here may be a late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of truth in ſome particular place, but it followeth not that either the error is truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath bin continued long, or the trueth error becauſe in that place it was receiued but lately: I like not this kind of reaſoning whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vſeth it, for it is not ſound neither ſtateth the conſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good mother, I know well you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the latin tongue, and therefore haue I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated many teſtimonies in latin, to giue you your due praiſe, this ability being not ordinary in women. And what you ſay, I thanke God hartely for, praying you to conſider that there be men on your ſide which ſo reaſon, and ſo ſay: Popery hath bin in england ſo long, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is truth: and the goſpel was reuiued but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6779:23"/>of late, therfore it is error, hereſy, apoſtaſie, and what not? Surely mother you haue touched the quick, ſuch arguing is looſe and ſtaieth not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cience, it followeth not, but is very chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh. Men may be called at the eleuenth houre, &amp; yet as truly called as they who were brought into the vineyard at the very firſt, and as fully ſhall be regarded, if they come then. <hi>The Lord may doe with his own as pleaſeth him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but what ſay you ſonne to our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? for that is a matter of moment: we were all baptiſed into the Romiſh faith, and vowed at the font to continue in the ſame. Howe then ſhall we ſtart from it without breaking our vow and offending both god and man?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In what fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> baptized.</note>S. Deare mother, here firſt I wiſh a lattiſe window in my breaſt, that the ioy of my heart for theſe your queſtions ſo fit and pertinent, &amp; I hope, profitable, might appeare vnto you: for they lead vs as it were by the hand to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of thoſe things which may fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie any Chriſtian heart. And who can tell what the Lord of mercy wil doe, who willeth not he death of a ſinner, but would haue al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaued &amp; come to the knowledge of the trueth. The Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who is the true ſheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſamp; biſhop of our ſoules, giue a bleſsing to our conference. Then to your doubt ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6779:24"/>well and to ſo good purpoſe moued I anſwere thus: God forbid that either all or any of vs had beene baptized into the Romiſh faith. You are deceiued and thoſe curſed charmers that whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſuch things to Gods people, and caſt ſuch ſtumbling blockes before their eyes to turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the right way, ſhall anſwer the Lord for ſo doing. You are taught and told that all thoſe who were baptiſed in thoſe times when popery was receiued by the realme of England were baptized into the Romiſh faith, which is not ſo: wherein appeared the great mercy and goodneſſe of God in preſeruing the Sacrament of entrance and admiſsion into Gods Church pure and ſound concerning the ſubſtance of it, euen in the greateſt darkeneſſe and authority of popery. This therefore I pray you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that we were all baptized in the time of popery into the ſame faith which nowe wee hold, and baptize children in, that is, into the faith of the 12. articles; for thus ſaid the prieſt then in latin, <hi>Credis in deum patrem, &amp;c.</hi> as the miniſter doth now in Engliſh, <hi>Doeſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in God the father almighty &amp;c.</hi> And the godfathers and godmothers anſwered then in the name of the child, <hi>Credo,</hi> as we doe nowe anſwere, <hi>All this I stedfastly beleeve.</hi> Then ſaid the prieſt in latin againe, as the miniſter
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6779:24"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h nowe in engliſh, <hi>wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou be baptized in this faith?</hi> they anſwered then for the childe, <hi>volo,</hi> we nowe, <hi>that is my deſire.</hi> Then tooke the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt water and ſaide in la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in, <hi>Ego baptizo te in nomine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atris, &amp;c.</hi> we ſay the ſame in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I baptize thee in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghost.</hi> And this beeing the ſubſtance of baptiſme, ſee howe the Lord preſerued it euen then pure and holy, and all one was baptiſme then and nowe concerning ſubſtance. Wilt thou be baptized in this faith, was not meant of the errour of the time, but of this faith now rehearſed contained in the 12. articles, which, except then it was ſome other becauſe it was latin, and nowe is ſaide in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, we ſee plainely they were then baptized in the ſame faith with vs, and that was a right true Catholicke faith, and not the Romiſh er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, that then ruled and were receiued of the ſtate. Our godfathers alſo holding the ſame faith, to wit, of the tvvelue articles, and vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chriſtened in the faith of our godfathers &amp; godmothers, ſo long as vve hold and continue in this our creede, vve continue in the ſame faith: if our godfathers and godmothers decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the time, held any other points in deede and trueth not agreeing vvith theſe 12. articles, vve anſvver that the ſacrament of our baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6779:25"/>doth not binde vs in all points to the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them who baptiſed vs, but in the faith of him in whoſe name we were baptiſed, and to the doctrine of the 12. articles then propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs: for, as if a man were chriſtened of an heretique, the baptiſme notwithſtanding were good, and the partie baptiſed not bound to hold that hereſie: ſo if our godfathers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which chriſtened vs were taught any thing not conſonant to Chriſtian doctrine, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is our baptiſme worſe for that, nor we bound to follow them in all points, eſpecially beeing caried away vnwittingly by ſubtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers from the truth. Thus good mother, is your doubt truely anſwered, and your heart, I truſt, aſſured, that by receiuing this faith novv eſtabliſhed through her Maieſties moſt bleſſed hand in England, you ſhall not depart from your vovve made at the ſome, but keepe it, nor ſvvarue from your faith vvherein you vvere baptized, and vvhich your godfathers and godmothers helde, but cleaue faſt vnto it to Gods great glorie, and your ovvn ſoules health.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Truely ſonne, you haue more ſatisfied me, then I thought in this matter any man li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing could haue done. And I ſee there is great miſtaking in many matters for vvant of loue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6779:25"/>one to endure talke with another. Whileſt I liue therefore, I will neuer refuſe conference, as I haue done: and I wiſh with all mine heart that others whome I knowe woulde doe the like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yea mother but the enemie knowing the good hereof, and what a fall his kingdome may thus take, laboureth to ſtop that willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in men and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trained to their errors, by taking othes of them not to doe it, &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning all manner of danger to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they doe it; and you would bleſſe your ſelfe to heare what groſſe praiſes they vtter of ignorance and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple obedience without ground or reaſon, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it belongeth no more to you or any other to aske a reaſon of their teachings, then it doth to the horſe to know why his maſter turneth his head this way or that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Mary God forbidde. It is but a ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I hope, as we are to light of beleefe on both ſides.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Truely Mother, no ſlaunder, nor mean mans doctrine, but a great Cardinall of Rome, although in this groſly carnall, the Cardinall Cuſanus. The place is knowen and cannot be denied. <hi>Excitationum, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 547. I ſhall ſhewe you his wordes if I can borrowe the booke.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:6779:26"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M</speaker>
               <p>There is a ſtory as I remember in the olde teſtament of one that would condition to haue their right eies, if he made peace with them. Surely this is to take our right eies from vs, not to ſuffer vs to vſe reaſon, and to aske for a ſatisfaction where we doubt.</p>
               <p>True it is, Mother; It was Naaſh the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monite that ſo anſwered the men of Iabeſh Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead:<note place="margin">1. Sam. c. 11.2.</note> and you moſt rightly apply it: full eaſie was it to rule and ouer rule, to mocke and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the ſtrong Sampſon, when once they had put out both his eies. To tell vs that ignorance is the mother of deuotion, when the Councell ſaith it is the mother of errour: to tell vs, that pearles may not be caſt before ſwine, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may not haue the ſcriptures in engliſh, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſpoken to all,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Search the ſcriptures:</hi> to tell vs we will become heretiques, if we meddle with the ſcriptures, when Chriſt ſaith <hi>you erre becauſe you know not the ſcriptures:</hi> ſurely this is not to wiſh vs to ſee, but to wiſh &amp; end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uour both to make and keepe vs blinde But I truſt the god of all mercie and goodneſſe, will both giue ſight, and keepe ſight in deſpite of all their fetching pollicies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>To returne then where we left, you ſay our fathers held the faith of the 12. articles, and were baptized in the ſame as we alſo are, ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6779:26"/>that we forſake not their faith, or the faith of our baptiſme, if we embrace the goſpell nowe preached, becauſe in nothing it is contrarie to theſe articles: notwithſtanding you ſay they were happely touched with ſome errours of the time. I pray you therefore what ſhall we ſay of them? were they damned or ſaued: if they were damned all, why may not we doe as they did, and hope of like mercy, god being the ſame ſtill, and as rich in goodneſſe and grace, as euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Your queſtion containeth two points, one of the ſaluation or damnation of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, another of the imitation of them.<note place="margin">what is beco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of our father</note> In both which I ſhall indeauour to giue you a tru anſwer. And touching the firſt I ſay, we ought not to ſit in iudgement vpon our fathers, for God was able to preſerue them euen in that darke time wherein they liued, as he preſerued the buſh in the middeſt of the flame, Daniel in the Lyons den, the three children in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and the Iſraelites in the red ſea: for all theſe were in mans eye ſubiect to daunger, and yet by a powerfull hand of an omnipotent god ſaued. And by the manifolde graces of god vouchſafed vnro our fathers, we may comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably hope that almighty God was willing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to preſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto an euerlaſting inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6779:27"/>and did that which he was able to doe vnto them: for they were good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and good women in their times, charitable and merciful, iuſt and true in their dealings, their honeſt word was better then many a mans bond, nowe: they brought vp their children in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt labour, not in idleneſſe and vanitie: they were giuen to hoſpitalitie, they hated pride &amp; loued plainnes, they loued the Church &amp; went duly vnto it: in a worde, as one ſaith of them, though they had, <hi>minùs ſcientiae, leſſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> yet they had <hi>plus conſcientiae, more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> wherfore that god that thus wrought in them by his guiding grace, I may well and cheerefully hope was further alſo good vnto them, and had mercy vpon them, pulling them out of the fire, as S. Iude ſaith: yea I haue heard of ſome that in thoſe darke times deliuered to their children ſome little treatiſes of <hi>Wickleff,</hi> and badde them keepe them ſecret and yet reade them and marke them, which argued a touch in their hearts more then the worlde ſaw, or they had ſtrength and boldneſſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to make ſhewe of. One mother I coulde name to you, that albeit ſhee did as the time then was, yet hadde ſhee an olde Pſalter in engliſh, and before her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, beeing younge would often reade on it,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6779:27"/>giuing them admonition in diuers points, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her motherly care, and by name when ſhee came to thoſe wordes, <hi>They haue eies and ſee not, feete haue they and goe not, hands and handle not, noſes and ſmell not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any breath in their mouthes: cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are all they that make them, and ſo are all they that put their truſt in them.</hi> Marke chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (would ſhee ſay) what thoſe Images you ſee in the Churches bee: they cannot ſee, goe, handle, or ſmell, they haue no life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may not worſhip or truſt in them, they are curſed that make them as you heare, and no doubt but there will come a time when they will bee taken away. By which we plainely ſee there was more in many of our good forefathers (for doe you thinke god was the god onely of this good woman?) more I ſay then the courſe of time yeelded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and therefore great teſtimonies that god ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them euen in the furnace and in the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons denne, that is, in the darke time, and time of daunger. Therefore farre be it from vs to iudge of them otherwiſe then well. They liue with the Lord God I moſt comfortably hope.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>This reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit of your elders ſonne, I truſt is a ſigne of Gods grace in you, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6779:28"/>your hope is grounded vpon good preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But why then may not wee nowe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their courſe as I ſaid, &amp; hope of like mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy alſo with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">why we may not imitate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r forefathers</note>S. Deare mother, let not me anſwere you, but heare and weigh with your ſelfe what S. Cyprian that learned and holy father anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, whoſe words are theſe: (I know you vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand them:) <hi>Ignoſci potuit ſimpliciter erranti, poſt inſpirationem verò &amp; revelatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem factam, qui in eo quo errauerat, perſeuerat ſine veniâ ignorantiae peccat, praeſumptione e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim at que obſtinatione ſuperatur.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinks I vnderſtand this ſentence to be thus much in engliſh; <hi>To one that of ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city erreth, pardon may be giuen: but who ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowledge reuealed and gratiouſly offered, continueth in his errour, that man or that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſinneth without hope of pardon for their ignorance, for he or ſhee is wholly carried away vvith preſumption and obſtinacie.</hi> Which ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce if it be that godly fathers, ſurely it ought to be well weighed of al that mean not to be ſo ouercome. And for my part I doe thinke and will thinke of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Surely mother they are his very wordes, and, for the ſence, well tranſlated by you. And bleſſed be God for your good taking of theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6779:28"/>graue ſpeeches of great lights and worthy tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in their times. The wordes are in his 62. epiſtle, as I ſhall ſhewe you when I come to the booke. And ſince my wordes finde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable fauour with you, let me, I pray; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew you how Satan hath alwaies vſed to deceiue men by theſe meanes, and howe God hath giuen councell to the contrary, Creſconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us the heretique ſaid to S. Auguſtin, <hi>Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers receiued this of their fathers before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And S. Auguſtin anſwered him, <hi>ſed errantes ab errantibus, but them men deceiued, receiued it of men that were deceiued before them.</hi> Even as the Iewes at this day receued of their fathers, and their fathers likewiſe receiued it before them of their fathers, and ſo from father to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſince the ſuffering of Chriſt, which is now almoſt 1567 yeares, that Chriſt did not riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, but that his diſciples came whileſt the watchmen ſlept, &amp; ſtole his body away. Now is this wicked falſhood true, becauſe by traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from father to ſonne it hath beene conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and taught amongſt the Ievves for ſo many yeres? god forbid. We beleeue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary as an article of our faith: and therefore you ſee this argument from our forefathers is dangerous and may carrie vs into great errors if vve take not heede. This notable anſvvere of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6779:29"/>S. Auguſtin and this worthy example woulde neuer be forgotten. Another great heretique called Eutiches, that denied the humanity of our Sauiour, beeing conuented for it in the Councell of Chalcedon, fled likewiſe to this defence and cried,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Sic à progenitoribus meis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiens credidi in hac fide genitus ſum &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratus deo, &amp; inea opto mori: this faith I haue receiued from my aunceſtoures and forefathers: in this faith I was borne and baptized, and in this faith I deſire to die.</hi> And yet that faith an horrible hereſie as you haue heard, denying that Ieſus Chriſt was man. Auxentius the Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an heretique made this his refuge, and told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſought his reformation, <hi>Quemadmodem ab infantiâ doctus ſum, ita crediat &amp; credo, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as from mine infancy I haue heene taught ſo I haue beleeued and doe beleeue.</hi> S. Hilary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth thus of him. By which examples wee plainely ſee what an olde ginne of Satan this is to intangle vs with the doings of our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to make vs beleeue that the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them in all things is a praiſe for vs, and that we ought not in any thing to ſlippe away from them. But it is not ſoe. God hath other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taught vs, auncient fathers haue othewiſe preached and written: and the matter of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation is weighty. We muſt beware,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6779:29"/>vnto the former examples ad, that of the Iewes ſo notable in the prophet, where beeing rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the prophet Ieremy for their Idolatry (God ſo commanding him) they flatly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as theſe heretiques before named, and as they of the Romiſh Church ſtill daily anſwere The worde which thou haſt ſpoken to vs in the name of the Lord, we will not heare it of thee but as our forefathers haue done, our kings and our princes in the city ot Iudah, ſo will we doe, euen whatſoeuer goeth out of our owne mouth, as to burne incenſe to the Queene of heauen, and to powre out drinke offrings vnto her: for then had we plentie of victualls, and were well and felt no euill: but ſince we left of to burne incenſe to the Queene of heauen, and to powre out drinke offerings vnto her: we haue ſcarceneſſe of all things, and haue bene conſumed by the ſword and famine &amp;c. I doubt not mother, but you marke this place well, for indeede it is a verie notable and pregnant example to this ende we nowe ſpeak of, and the words are as it we heard all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Catholicks ſpeake together, ſo iumpe they with them. And ſo like is Satan to himſelfe in his trickes and deuiſes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Gods people. But nowe what ſaith God? Doeth be like of this anſwere and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6779:30"/>of this heady and vnadviſed following of their aunceſtoures. No, No, neither euer will he like of it to the worldes ende. Reade I beſeech you the chapter your ſelfe, and you ſhall ſee the fierce wrath of the Lord againſt them for this anſwere, and for this doing. He ſweareth by his great name (a dreadfull puniſhment) that he will not vouchſafe to haue his name any more mentioned by them: but he will watch ouer them for euill and not for good, till they all be conſumed by the ſworde and by the famine with an vtter deſtruction. This is the liking that God hath of following others before vs, and of alleadging their examples without due care and conſideration of their doings, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were anſwerable to Gods word the rule of his liking and pleaſure yea or no. By his Prophet Ezechiel againe he inſtructeth vs of his pleaſure in this matter,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 20. v. 18.</note> and deliuereth it for his abſolute commandement. <hi>In ſtatutis patru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nolite ambulare, vvalke ye not in the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your fathers, neither obſerue their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:</hi> meaning, raſhly, vnadviſedly, hand ouer head, without examination, howe theſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and manners pleaſed God. For ſo ſaieth the prophet, <hi>you may defile your ſelves either vvith Idols,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> .19.</note> 
                  <hi>or ſome other thing diſpleaſing to God. But if you vvill euer be ſure and ſafe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6779:30"/>the true rule and the onely right vvay. I am the Lord your God, vvalke in my statutes, &amp; keepe my commandements &amp;c.</hi> Which ſound counſell the godly father had his eye vpon, when he ſaide, <hi>Non debemus attendere quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis ante nos faciendum putauerit, ſedquid qui ante omnes eſt Christus prior fecerit, vve may not regard what ſome before vs thought meete to be done, but what he who vvas before all men Ieſus Chriſt our deare Sauiour did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> that that is our rule in whatſoeuer we are to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him. I cannot omit to remember Lactanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us his wordes in this matter, <hi>Deorum cultores libentèr errant, &amp; ſtultitiae favent ſuae, à qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſirationem requiras per ſuaſionis eius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſtitut. l. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nulla poſſunt reddere, ſed ad maiorum iudicia confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giunt, quòd illi ſapientes fuerint. The vvorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of many Gods</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doe vvillingly erre, and favour their owne folly: of vvhome if you aske a reaſon of their perſwaſion and opinion, they can giue none, but ſtraight flie to the iudgement of their forefathers, ſaying they vvere wiſe men &amp;c.</hi> And is not this the verie anſwer of Romiſh Catholicks at this day? Can they giue any reaſon a number of them but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this now mentioned of heretickes and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatours? <hi>I vvas borne and baptized in this faith, and mine owne father and mother char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6779:31"/>me vpon their bleſsing, to be of this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp;c.</hi> they were as wiſe men and women as we and ſuch like. But how good theſe anſwers bee, you ſee, if you either regard ſcripture, or fathers, to be taught by them. Lactantius nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth this folly we ſee by his words and euer it ſhall be derided. Our ſoules coſt more then that ſhould pinne them on any mens ſleeues, were they neuer ſo neere or deare vnto vs. Clemens Alexand hath the like good ſpeach. <hi>Alii dicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, im pium eſt ſi non colamus ea quae nobis tradita ſunt à patribus noſtris, &amp; religionem praevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camur à matoribus datam. Hac ratione ſicuius pater latro fuerit, aut ſicuius, leno, à patribus ſibi traditam conſuetudinem mutare no debet, nec ad meliorem viam à paternis erroribus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocari, Others ſay it is a great wickedneſſe, if we worſhip not thoſe things which are by our forefathers deliuered vnto vs, and we betray the religion of our fathers: but by this reaſon if any mans father were a theife or a bawde, he ought not to chaunge the cuſtome deriued from his father nor be reduced to a better way from his fathers errour.</hi> Thus derideth he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine this fonde kinde of argument. <hi>My fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ſo, and ſo his father before him again, therefore I will doe ſo anâ vvill not bee perſvvaded.</hi> Yea aſſuredly thus haue euer
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6779:31"/>all truely inſtructed derided it. And it neuer was, nor neuer ſhall be a fitte aunſwere for a childe of God. When I thinke of this matter ſometimes I make a compariſon betwixt the body and the ſoule, and I aske of a Romiſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke, whether if his father and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his aunceſtoures had a bodily diſeaſe whereof they died for want of skill to cure it, he nowe hauing the ſame ſucceſsiuely after them, and the cure well knowen, would yet wilfully die of his infirmity as his forefathers did, rather then ſwarue from the example and be cured; He will anſwere no. And yet in the matter of the ſoule which is farre aboue the bodie hath not grace to conſider what an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd anſwer it is to alleadge his father, vnleſſe he know by the rule of gods word, that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed was to be followed. So you ſee (deare mother) both your queſtions anſwered, and how it is no new matter but a very ancient ſubtiltie to entangle men and womens mindes with the examples of their forefathers, becauſe naturally we all reuerence and loue thoſe of whome we are deſcended. But it is no right way: For we both may and ought ſometimes to diſſent from them, and yet not ſit in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon them as though they were dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, God beeing indeede able to ſaue them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6779:32"/>as we haue heard: neither ought we thereby to take occaſion of preſumption to condemne the grace offered vs, though denied to others, as we ought not to refuſe a bodily medicine to ſaue our life, becauſe our fathers know it not. Surely if they had had the light that is vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed vs, they would haue excelled vs, as farre as angels excell men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee ſonne gods ſpirit bloweth where it liſteth, and happy is the man and woman whoſe eare he openneth. To heare is good, and either to ſtoppe our ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, or to harden our heart with a premeditate opinion is moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: for as the Apoſtle perſwadeth to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality, becauſe ſo men haue receiued angels into their houſes: ſo by hearing is god receiued who made the angels, and by refuſing to heare the doore is ſhut vpon him moſt dangerouſly and be excluded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>O deare Mother giue your owne fleſh and blood leaue with knees of heart bowed before the Lord to reioyce for this your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeech, to praiſe the name of the moſt high, whoſe mercy hath neither bottom nor mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and to beſeech him for his ſweete ſonnes ſake to goe forward in mercy and pitty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his deceiued children, that they may ſee their ſaluation in Ieſus Chriſt, embrace the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6779:32"/>trueth and be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>To this your prayer ſonne, I ſay with all mine heart, amen. But yet I haue not done with you. I haue heard ſome ſay, that if this way that you ſo diſlike, to follow the church of Rome, and to beleeue as we are taught by the ſucceſſours of Peter, were to goe aſtraie, why hath it not beene noted ſo till now of late yeares. Can any of you tell where or vnder what Pope or Emperour papiſtrie firſt began, and what Churches then complained of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good Mother your queſtions ſtill are to good purpoſe;<note place="margin">who firſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Rome to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for this is an high point with diuers popiſh writers, and theſe thinke they haue plunged vs, when they haue made this de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde. But I am nowe comforted with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of your readineſſe to heare what on our ſide is anſwered, which is thus: That if theſe falſe perſwaders thinke (as appeareth by this queſtion they doe) that the Church ſtanding poſſeſſed of a true religion, there cannot ariſe a falſe, but that ſome either many or fewe muſt rebuke it; it is not ſo in ſuch errours as creepe in at the beginning by hypocriſie, &amp; by a great ſhewe of holineſſe, as poperie did, but onely in groſſe and apparent errours it is ſo. Nowe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie is called of the Apoſtle, a miniſterie, and why? becauſe it is not open to euery eye, but
<pb facs="tcp:6779:33"/>vnder a colour and cloake of holineſſe ſo conueieth it ſelfe into mens hearts, and into the worlde, that it is not obſerued and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of many, and ſcarce by any. Againe, as a building maketh no ſhewe till it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ground, ſo this ſynagogue for a time was not noted, when yet the worke men laboured harde to raiſe it and builde it. Thirdly, wee are admoniſhed and tolde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of this errour, that ſo ſlie, ſo colourable and ſo hypocriticall it ſhould be, as the very elect thereby, if it were poſsible, ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. Fourthly in reaſon and experience wee ſee and knowe that tares in the corne are not noted till they bee come vppe, the graſſe is not ſeene growing, but when it is gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. And therefore to ſet this down that no falſe religion, no errour of hereſie may creepe into the church, but at the very firſt it muſt be noted of ſome, is not true, &amp; eſpecially of this errour of poperie: for it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred not all at once, but by degrees in diuers ages, and theſe degrees ſo ſmall that they they could not more be diſcerned then the graſſe growing. The hypocriticall ſhewe of devotion and good intent letted greatly: the woolfe in a ſheepes skinne may deceiue. Again it is well knowen that theſe primitiue times
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6779:33"/>were greatly exerciſed with open, groſſe, and apparent hereſies, ſeeking the ouerthrowe of the faith directly &amp; manifeſtly, as of Ebion, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inthus, Arrius, and others Diuers, of the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whereof were of great giftes, and ſo their doings were dangerous: vpon which the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eyes were bent, that it was not poſsible to obſerue little ones creeping in ſo colourably as I haue ſaide, and ſo hypocritically. If any did obſerue ſomewhat then, yet neuer thought they that ſuch ſmall declinings would grow to ſuch an iſſue as nowe we ſee, and therefore were leſſe carefull to write of them; and if they did write, ſo many and ſo great haue bene the loſſes of bookes ſince that time by perſecutions and troubles,<note place="margin">That the biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops of Rome did vſe to bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all bookes croſſing their errours, vide Concil. Rom. Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. ſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Trident. Bellar. Tom 1. contr. 5. l. 3. de laicis, c. 20.</note> and ſundry confuſions in the world, that well they might periſh and bee loſt Moreouer the biſhops of Rome beeing in credit with the Emperours had euer op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunitie to ſuppreſſe, deface, and alter wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, roules, and recordes againſt them, as they thought good, whoſe conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces could brooke ſuch dealings well inough, as we ſee by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the councell of Nice falſified by them to their perpetuall ſhame. Finally the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of diuers good bishops of Rome at the firſt, did ſo ſticke in the mindes of men, that for their ſakes the reſt a great
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6779:34"/>while after were the better thought of and not ſuſpected as they deſerued, who indeede ſucceeded in place, but not in vertue and pietie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne theſe be good reaſons I confeſſe, why the beginning might not be ſo well mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: but yet if it had beene ſo falſe a religion as now is ſaide, it could not but haue beene mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of ſome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good mother if what I haue ſaide bee well weighed, it doth fully prooue what I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, namely, that errour may creepe in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of deuotion by ſmall degrees, in the time of greater groſſe hereſies and not be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a time. But if ſo much may not ſuffice, we anſwere further to your queſtion, that the miſterie of Papiſtrie beeing antichriſtianity, began euen in the Apoſtles times Claudius be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Emperour of Rome, and ſo continued increaſing vntill the time of Sigiſmund, who procured the councell of Conſtance, in which the lay people were robbed of the cup. So haue you the Emperour vnder whome it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne. But for the pope we vſe to craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don id we cannot ſhewe him certainly, becauſe then there were three popes, &amp; no man could tell which was the right, but euerie man ſpake as he was affected to one of them. And for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6779:34"/>againſt it the ſtories make it well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, that in the time of Seuerus Emperour, Victor biſhop of Rome bewraying an ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſire of ſuperiority ouer other biſhopps,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. 5. c. 25</note> Irenaeus the ancient father, Biſhop then of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Polycrates, and many others reprooued him. Afterward in the daies of Theodoſius, Honorius, and Arcadius, the biſhops of Rome Innocentius, Bonifacius, Sozimus, Anaſtaſius, and Caeleſtine vſurping more openly &amp; ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully forging the decree of the Nicene councel were reprooued and complained of by the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Africa in open councell, the forgerie detected, and decrees made that none in Africa ſhould appeale to any biſhops ouer the ſea, and that the biſhop of the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea ſhould not bee called prince of prieſtes, or by any ſuch name of pride, but onely biſhop of the firſt ſea. After this againe when Iohn of Conſtantinople in the daies of Mauritius vſurped the title of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall biſhop, Gregory the biſhop of Rome reprooueth it himſelfe, and with ſuch vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of words ratleth him vp for it, as no more can be ſaid againſt that point of popery. Then was Mauritius cruelly murdered by his ſeruant Phocas, and the Empire giuen to Pho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cas, vnder whome Bonifacius of Rome gotte that proud title. But the Church of Rauenna
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6779:35"/>with others complained of ſuch pride, and would not be ſubiect for many yeares. Many more haue cried out as they could and noted this falling away from truth and pietie to pride and antichriſtianity. But good Mother, ponder with your ſelfe how needles this is to be ſtood vpon, where there is euidence of fault and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood. Doe we not account it folly when we ſee tares in the fielde, to denie they be tares, vnleſſe we knowe who ſowed them, what day and houre &amp;c. If an houſe be on fire, wee ſeeke to quench it, and ſtand not to aske who ſet it one fire. A theife taken with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is puniſhed. Popery compared with the doctrine of the Apoſtles appeareth to bee tares, and we offer that iſſue if we prooue it, what though we knowe not when the tares were caſt into the good fielde? Shall not a white head be taken ſo to be vnleſſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe beginning of white haires be known? A chinke in a wall is ſpied and mended, but the beginning vſually vnknown. When the Scribes and Phariſes had corrupted religion, what bookes doe we reade to be written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? How able were Ioſeph, Simeon, Marie, Anna, &amp;c. to confute them? Falſhood is falſhood though no man write againſt it. And therefore let the doctrine of poperie he ſifted
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6779:35"/>whether it be ſound or no, and the beginning let goe, of which yet you ſee what I haue ſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne, you haue ſaid much, and ſtill I wiſh that one of vs would heare another more then we do. I ſee, I ſee it is profitable: god hath commaunded meanes, and liketh meanes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Mother, many a good man and woman that nowe liueth in ignorance woulde heare and reade, but that they are ſo terrified in holes and corners by falſe charmers vnder the paine of excommunication not to doe it, nor to conferre with any. Yea they are often ſnared with an oath not to doe it: and all to keepe them in darkneſſe, becauſe the hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hauke is quieteſt, and Sampſon when his eies be out may be mocked and vſed at will: but the Lord is able to touch his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts to thinke of their craft, and caſt from them ſuch deceitfull workes which I beſeech him to doe euen with ſpeede. For the impietie and boldneſſe of theſe wicked char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers is great, and worthily reprooued by S. Hierome, who ſaith, of ſome in his time that they did <hi>tantam ſibi aſſumere authoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in Eſai. l. 9. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>vt ſiue dextra docerent ſiue ſiniſtra, id eſt: ſiue bona ſiue malanolint diſcipulos ratione diſcutere, ſed ſe praeceſſores ſequi, ſome did take ſuch autority</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:6779:36"/>vpon them, that whether they taught right or wrong, good or badde, they would not haue their auditours to examine it, but to followe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but it is a great matter ſonne, in our eyes, that the Church of Rome hath alwaies beene a viſible ſtate maintaining that doctrine, viſible I ſay and ſtill appearing and knowne, whereas your church before Luthers time, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was not at all, or was hidde, as ſome ſay, and your doctrine not receiued by publike authoritie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>But good mother, you know trueth is trueth although the whole world were ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. And therefore ſtill I wiſh your eye bent not vpon the fauour of the world, for that is commonly againſt the good and for the badde, but vpon the face of almightie God, his good pleaſure, and the rule thereof his worde. And then for anſwere to this obiected, which ſeemeth ſo ſtrong a bulwarke in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many Papiſts:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> nor alwaies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſible.</note> firſt I ſay, that the true church is not alwaies viſible in the worlde as they take viſible, that is, glorious in credit, and fauour, ſupported by authority of worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, ſo that all people may know whether to reſort vnto it. For the Church is either Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike 1. vniuerſall or particular. The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6779:36"/>or vniuerſall church cannot be ſeene, and therfore we beleeue it as an article of our faith. <hi>Credo ſanctam eccleſiam Catholicam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Symb. Apoſt.</note> 
                  <hi>I beleeue that there is an holy Catholike Church,</hi> not as ſome would haue it, <hi>I giue credit to the church and beleeue what ſoeuer it teacheth,</hi> for then it ſhould be <hi>Credo Eccleſiae</hi> not <hi>Credo Eccleſiam.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sentent. l. 3. diſtinct. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> There is great difference ſaith <hi>P.</hi> Lumbard fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing S. Auſten betwixt <hi>Credere Deum, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere Deo,</hi> and <hi>Creaere in Deum:</hi> the firſt is to beleeue that there is a God, the ſecond to giue credance vnto God, and to beleeue all that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u which he ſpeaketh, the third, to rely vpon god, and to put our confidence in him for protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and bleſsing. So doubtleſſe may I ſay that there is an apparent difference betwixt <hi>Crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Eccleſiam Catholicam, Credere Eccleſiae Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae,</hi> and <hi>Creaere in Eccleſiam Catholicam:</hi> the firſt is to be aſſuredly perſwaded and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that there is a Catholike Church, which is the meaning of the article, as the very phraſe of ſpeach ſheweth, and the other articles follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, <hi>Credo communionem Sanctorum, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that there is a communion of Saints, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do remiſsionem peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I beleeue that there is a remiſsion of ſinnes, Credo carnis reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem, I beleeue that there is a reſurrection of the fleſh, &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>Credere Eccleſiae
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6779:37"/>catholicae,</hi> is to giue credit vnto the Catholike Church, and to embrace as trueth whatſoeuer the Church ſhall propound vnto vs, which can not be the ſenſe of the article, except we will both confound theſe two phraſes <hi>Credere Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cſleſiam,</hi> and <hi>Credere Eccleſiae,</hi> ſo accurately di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by the maſter of the ſentences and S. Auguſtin, and make the wordes of men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with Gods word. The third, <hi>Credere in Eccleſiam Catholicam,</hi> is wholly to depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Catholike Church, which we cannot make the ſenſe of the article without violence to the wordes and great blaſphemie to God. Thus much by the way and by your gentle patience, good mother, of this article, and the true meaning of it in generall, becauſe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking thereof hath miſled ſome into errour. Now to returne ſeeing we beleeue the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall or Catholike Church, it followeth that it can not be ſeene.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eb. 11.1.</note> For faith, as the Apoſtle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>is the ground of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeene.</hi> Not ſeene I ſay againe and intreat you to marke the worde. And that a particular Church is not alwaies ſeene, the ſtorie of Elias prooueth pregnantly, who could not ſee one, and therefore was we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his life,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing. 19.18.</note> whereas God had kept vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, euen then when he complained and in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6779:37"/>that place where he liued, yea in the middeſt of that people of whome he complained 7000. that had not bowed their knees vnto Ball. What may we thinke of theſe 7000. among the tenne trikes of Iſrael? were they not Gods people worſhipping him in ſpirit and in truth? or is not the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſufficiet to make a church? Surely the number might well make ſeuen glorious particular Churches,<note place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the Apoſtle ſaieth of them, firſt that God had kept them to himſelfe, ſecondly that they were his people, thirdly that he knewe them before, to wit, in his eternall councell, and almighty God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his prophet acknowledged them as his beloued, and promiſed his protection vnto them, that they ſhould be ſafely kept. Reaſons,<note place="margin">1. Reg. c. 19.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.17. &amp; 18.</note> I ſuppoſe ſufficient both for number and weight to prooue that God had his church in that place, and at that ſelfe ſame time, when &amp; where the prophet Elias complained for want of a Church and fellowe members to worſhip God with him. O if ſo many ſo deare vnto god at one time in one countrie worſhipping the true God, truly, by the teſtimony of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, were hidde from ſo great a Prophet, why may we not thinke that in the many mightie nations of Chriſtendome there haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede beene many thouſands more belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6779:38"/>to God then the eie of any man could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne. S. Auguſtin ſaith, <hi>Aliquando in ſola do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Noah Eccleſia erat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l. 128.</note> 
                  <hi>in ſolo Lot &amp; domo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius Eccleſia erat, in ſolo Enoch Eccleſia erat, Sometimes the Church was onely in Noah his houſe, ſometime in Abraham alone, ſometime in Lot alone and his houſe, ſometime onely in Enoch.</hi> Therefore neither a particular church is euer ſo viſible, as papiſts would make it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it lieth hidden ſometimes in one houſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in one man. Aſſuredly <hi>S.</hi> Auguſtin was farre from that opinion when he wrot thus:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nit. Eccl. c3. c. 16. aſch. c. 14.</note> Looke therefore howe Chriſt was knowen when he was vpon earth, ſo is his Church, namely by the worde, not by the outwarde Pompe and ſhewe. Shee cannot be hidde from thoſe that ſtill diligently ſeeke her in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, where onely, I ſay againe, the certaine knowledge of her is to be found.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 10.</note> Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhee is compared by S. Auguſtin and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, to the moone, which is often hidde, and he acknowledgeth that ſhee may be ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret that the members know not one another. Perſecutions haue bin ſo great, that the world ſawe not for a long time together ſuch an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhewe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g. de. bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. cont. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 6. c. 4.</note> as Popery ſpeaketh of. Diocleſian and Maximinian boaſted that they had vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly aboliſhed the ſuperſtition of Chriſt (as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6779:38"/>they call it) and name of Chriſtians. The like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueliſh boaſting made Nero in his time, where was then this viſible face of the Church ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious? that notable place of the Apoſtle, what ſhall we ſay to it? They were tried by moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.36. &amp;c.</note> and ſcourgings, yea moreouer by bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and impriſonment, they were ſtoned, they were hewen a ſunder, they were tempted, they were ſlaine with the ſword, they wandred vp and downe in ſheepe skinnes, and in goat skins, beeing deſtitute, afflicted and tormented: who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the world was not worthy of, they wandred in wilderneſſes and mountaines and dennes, &amp; caues of the earth. Were not theſe the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God? were not theſe the Church? what out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pompe had theſe men in the worlde, to mooue others ledde by ſuch inducements to reſort vnto them? O folly therefore to dreame of any ſuch thing! Howe differeth it from that errour of the diſciples, exſpecting an earthly kingdome of their maſter, and worldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments for themſelues That viſion of the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man forced to flie into the wilderneſſe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide the rage of antichriſt,<note place="margin">Apoc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> doth it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince my conſcience, that the Church is hidde ſometimes from mens eies! Howe can that Church be ſaide to flie into the wilderneſſe, which hath alwaies a viſible face, a viſible place
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6779:39"/>a viſible grace and glorie, a great companie of fauourers, might, power, authority, &amp;c. were not Chriſt and his followers on earth the Church? had they any ſuch ſhewe? Nay they were poore, baſe, and not regarded in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the Scribes, Phariſees, high prieſts, and that rabble. <hi>You ſhall be hated of all men for my ſake, &amp;c:</hi> ſaith our Sauiour of his Church: and is this to be viſible euer in the world in manner and forme now often mentioned? who ſeeth not that it is farre from it. And thus I hope I haue ſufficiently cleared this firſt point, that the Church is not alwaies viſible, as they meane viſible, which may ſuffice for anſwer to this vaine obiection of theirs, as vtterly ouerthrowing the ground thereof: yet I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere further firſt to their Church, that no Romiſh Catholicke liuing (and I pray you conſider well what I ſay) ſhall euer be able to prooue that there was any viſible Church for fiue or ſixe hundred yeares after Chriſt, which maintained all or the cheife points of popery, wherein they differ from vs. Then for our Church we truely affirme that it was long before Luther, euen in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church. For we ſtand vpon this, that we embrace and profeſſe onely that doctrine which ſpringeth as the water of life out of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6779:39"/>the ſanctuarie, that is, out of the writings of the prophets and Apoſtles, and therefore that our Church doth not differ ſaue that in degree of excellency from thoſe famous churches plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and watered by the Apoſtles themſelues; which ſhall yet more manifeſtly appeare by the doctrine it ſelfe duly conſidered, the main points whereof, as hath been already touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in another place, are theſe, 1. Concerning the morall lawe of God compriſed in tenne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, that it is the perfect rule of righteouſnes, wherein we ſee as in a Chriſtall glaſſe, both what we ſhould doe, and what we doe not, and howe farre ſhort we are of that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which is required at our handes by god. 2. The doctrine of repentance, that finding of our ſelues tranſgreſſoures of Gods diuine lawe, and guiltie of his wrath, wee ſhould in due humilitie and contrition of heart throwe downe our ſelues at the throne of his grace, and in the anguiſh of our ſoules confeſſe our iniquities and rebellions againſt our ſelues, and euerie man ſay with the poore Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, <hi>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> 3. The doctrine of faith, that trauelling thus and groaning vnder the burden of our ſinnes, wee ſhould goe vnto our Sauiour for eaſe, comfort, and refreſhing, that is, that we ſhould
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6779:40"/>ſteadfaſtly beleeue that he died for our ſinnes and roſe againe for our iuſtification and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluation.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 4.</note> 4. the doctrine of good workes and a godly life, that we ought euer to bee carefull to abound in good workes and haue our conuerſation in heauen. 5. The doctrine of praier that we ſhould in all our neceſsities call vpon God in the name of his ſonne, as our bleſſed Sauiour hath taught vs in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 3.</note> and eſpecially that we ſhould frequent the houſe of God, by publike praier to ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and by his word to heare him ſpeak vnto vs for inſtruction. 6. The doctrine of the Sacraments, Baptiſme and the Lords ſupper. 7. Laſtly, the twelve articles of our creede, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in God &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are the pillars and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our religion, yea the very ſoule and life of our Church, and all of them founded &amp; grounded vpon the rocke Ieſus Chriſt, and his ſacred word, and without controuerſie the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eſſence and beeing of all Churches that haue been euer or ſhall be to the ende of the world. Wherefore when our aduerſaries ask vs (as they doe very often) where was your church before Luther, we may well anſwere, as our Sauiour did in the Goſpell by another queſtion, <hi>videlicet,</hi> Theſe points of doctrine before mentioned were they before Luthers
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6779:40"/>time or no? If they will anſvvere vs to this, we vvill anſvver them, yea they ſhall be forced to anſvver themſelues, that this doctrine is of god and from heauen, and that there neuer vvanted ſome to profeſſe it publikly in all partes or the moſt of Chriſtendome, ſince the happy time of our bleſſed Sauiour: and therefore that our Church hath alvvaies bin a viſible ſtate though not ſo ſtately as they boaſt of theirs to their ovvne ſhame, if Saint Auguſtin may be iudge, vvho calleth Rome in regard of this pompe and pride the Weſtern Babylon, the ſecond Babylon, another Babylon,<note place="margin">de cinit. d 16. c. 17. l. 1 22.27</note> the daughter of the former Babylon the earthly citie. Yet for their further ſatisfaction <hi>I</hi> further aske of them: doe not they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſay they beleeue all theſe for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer points? doe they not ſtand vpon it that they haue euer ſo profeſſed? Is there any thing in there religion of more moment and vveight or any other part of doctrine beſides theſe, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſarie to ſaluation? vvhy then doe they aske vs vvhere and by vvhome this religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ours vvas profeſſed before Luthers time? May vve not vvell and charitably affirme that it vvas profeſſed in Fraunce. Spaine, and Italy: yea in Rome euer ſince firſt Rome embraced the goſpell preached by the Apoſtles? Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I am perſvvaded that many thouſands
<pb facs="tcp:6779:41"/>euen nowe in theſe countries where the popes keyes preuaile, doe truely hold the 12. articles of the Apoſtles creede and Athanaſius his creede, which he calleth the Catholike faith, with all the other points of doctrine ſet down before, which if they doe, holding the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, though they build vpon it woode, hay,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 3.</note> or ſtubble, that is ſome erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, yet they are the true Church of God and ſhallbe ſaued. A pearle, is a pearle, though in an heape of duſt, wine is wine though min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with water, and wheate is wheate, though couered with much chaffe: and is not the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of godlineſſe whereof Paul ſpeaketh, god manifeſted in the fleſh,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 3.</note> iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Gentils, beleeued on in the world, receiued vp in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſtill the myſterie of godlineſſe, and that trueth and ſure foundation whereo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe of god is builded, though matter vnſutable vnto it be laide vpon it? yes verely. And therefore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church of Rome hath euer held the miſterie of godlineſſe though mingled with many dregs of mens inuentions, I doubt not but God hath euer had a people amongſt them and a true Church more then 7000. which haue not bowed the knee vnto Baal.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6779:41"/>what we are to thinke of their leaders and teachers which indeed haue corrupted this doctrine with their owne leauen, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by all meanes to ſhut vp and obſcure this myſterie, is another queſtion, eſpecially for thoſe that haue done it wilfully and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly, and died in that malice. But of the reſt thus we iudge and thus we anſwere, that ſo many as truely holde and profeſſe all the former articles of doctrine (as I aſſure my ſelfe many doe) are fellowe members with vs in the ſame myſticalll bodie whereof Chriſt is the head. And therefore our church hath euer beene in theirs, though not euer ſo manifeſt to the eye of the worlde as it was for the ſpace of the firſt fiue hundred yeares. Me thinkes this anſwere ſhould well content them and fully ſatisfie them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo charitable towards them. But to giue them an anſwere of their owne and by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to let them ſee that the true Church is not alwaies ſo viſible as they pretende. They knowe that nowe in England they haue not authoritie to countenance their religion and Church, and yet they ſay that they haue a Church amongeſt vs, and where they dare well ſay it, they are bold to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6779:42"/>ſay it is a great one, yea the greter part, though I truſt they ſhall neuer prooue it in that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Why then in perſecution and when the Lord puniſheth the vnthankefulneſſe of men with taking awaie our publike and autoriſed aſſemblies, may not we as well haue a church holding the true faith of Chriſt according to his word, as they now a flocke cleauing to the Biſhop of Rome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Rome hath alwaies beene called the Mother Church, and they doe ioyne with that.<note place="margin">Rome is not he mother Church.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Howe can Rome be the mother church, when ſhee is later then thoſe firſt churches of Hieruſalem, and Antioche? Can a mother be yonger then her daughters, or her daughters elder then their mother? The very ſcriptures teach vs that all churches, and euen Rome it ſelfe haue riſen out of the Churche of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. <hi>Fou out of Sion ſhall his lavve come, and the word from Hieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You anſwer me well that Rome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the mother Church of al, becauſe other churches haue beene before her. Neuertheles of this Church of England ſhee is rightly the mother, becauſe this land receiued the faith fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her, firſt by Eleutherius the Pope and martir, who ſent Daminianus and Fugatius to teach
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6779:42"/>it to the Britanes at the requeſt of their king who was then Lucius, and after by Gregory the great, who ſent Auguſtine and Melitus with other holy prieſts to teach our aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours the engliſh, who then were planted here and had remooued the Brittaines into an other corner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Deare mother all this you are taught and told by them who abuſe gods people bought with his pretious blood. But it hath beene an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered truely, that this can not be ſo. For firſt Eleuth confeſſeth in his anſwer to king Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us his meſſage, that he had the ſcriptures, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were the lawes of God, farre more to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded then the Romane lawes: he praiſeth his zeale and telleth him, that out of the ſcriptures with the aduiſe of his counſell he might draw conuenient lawes for his kingdome he beeing in his owne land Chriſts vicar &amp;c. Howe then was Eleutherius his firſt Apoſtle? Againe doth not Nicephorus plainely ſaie in his ſtory, <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Zelotes doctrinam Evangelij ad occidentalium Oceanum in ſulas<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Brittanicas perfert.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 2. c. 40</note> Simon Zelotes carried the doctrine of the goſpell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the weſt Ocean ſea and vnto the Iſlandes of Britraine. This was before Eleutherius Doe not others write that Ioſeph of Arimathea did it? hat. S. Paul in his paſſage this way into Spain
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6779:43"/>did it, and alleadge authors for it? Might not the Greekes doe it, or ſome others, ſince eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently it appeareth by Eleutherius his own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, he was not the firſt? Then for Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine and the reſt doe not theſe plaine teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the fathers vſually alleadged to this end ſatisfie any man liuing not way warde, that this land had the faith before him and them. Tertullian liued about the yeare of our Lord 210. And his words are theſe. <hi>Brittannorum in acceſſa Romanis loc a ſubduntur Chriſto.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Iudaeos.</note> The <hi>countries of Britane which the Romanes coulde never attaine vnto are now ſubiect to Chriſt.</hi> Origen about the yeare 212 writeth,<note place="margin">Ezech. hom.</note> 
                  <hi>Terra Brittanniae in religionem Chriſti conſenſit. The land of Britane hath yeelded to Chriſt his religion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Apolog. 2.</note> Athanaſius about the yeare three hundred thirtie foure hath the like. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the Emperour maketh mention in his time of Chriſtian Churches in Britane.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od. l. 1. c. 10.</note> This was about the yeare 330. S. Hilary in his time intituleth his letter, <hi>Clericis Toloſanis &amp; provinciarum Britannicarum epiſcopis.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. de Synod.</note> 
                  <hi>To the Clergi of Toloſa and to the biſhops of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane.</hi> This was about the yeare 360. S. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome of his time ſaieth.<note place="margin">m. quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riſtus ſit de</note> 
                  <hi>Et in ſulae Britanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae extra hoe mare ſitae &amp; in ipſo Oceano poſitae ſenſerunt virt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tem verbi dei. The Iſlands
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6779:43"/>of Britane beeing in the very Ocean and farre out of this our ſea haue felt the power of Gods vvord.</hi> This he wrotte about anno 400. Theodoret ſaith, <hi>Huic fidei conſenſerunt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Eccleſiae, quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in Hiſpania ſunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſtor. l. 4. c.</note> 
                  <hi>quae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in Britannia. To this faith haue agreed all the Churches both of Spaine and Britane.</hi> What can be more plaine and more fully prooued if we be not wilfull. Now all theſe fathers and writers liued ſundrie yeares before the ariuall of Auſtine the monke and his fellowes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they by no meanes coulde bee the firſt planters and publiſhers of the faith in this land. Gildas writeth that in the time of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius this land was Chriſtian.<note place="margin">Hiſt. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g. l. 2 c. 2.</note> Beda writeth that in his time and almoſt a thouſand yeares after Chriſt Eaſter was kept here in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land after the manner of the Eaſt Church in the full moone what day in the weeke ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it fell on, and not on the ſunday as nowe we doe, whereby it is very manifeſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the firſt preachers in this lande came more rather out of the Eaſt, then from Rome. Therefore by all theſe proofes and arguments Rome is not the mother Church of England, for it had the trueth long before Eleutherius or Auſtin. I ſpare to ſhewe the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6779:44"/>bloodie crueltie of this Auſtin (whome the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts make an Apoſtle) with other his foule vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of pride and diſdaine, &amp;c. our ſtories ſhewe it: and I may haue other occaſſion hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſonne, I will nowe goe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with you in theſe pointes: but I will put a caſe or two, and tell me your minde. What if a Catholike be ſworne to perſiſt in the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Church of Rome, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt, howe can ſuch an one without plaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury take another courſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede this is their diueliſh practiſe and pollicy in theſe daies, to ſteale the hearts and loyaltie of the people from their prince, as Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon did from his father, but came to a foule ende; to creepe into houſes, and lead captiue ſimple women,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 6.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaieth, to ſnare them with oathes and vowes and promiſes, &amp; whatſoeuer they can deuiſe,<note place="margin">cont. Val.</note> wherein they tread in the ſteps of the olde Valentinian here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques worthily taxed by Tertullian, of whom that learned father ſaith: <hi>Aditum priùs cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, they firſt torment their ſchollers, at their entrance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne diſcipulis quidem proprijs antè co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittant quàm ſuos fecerint, they commit not their miſteries and doctrine, no not to their ovvne diſciples, before they haue made them
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6779:44"/>their owne. Habent artificium quo priùs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadeant quàm edoceant: they haue a tricke of legerdemaine, firſt to perſvvade before they teach.</hi> Even as nowe our Ieſuits and ſeminarie prieſts when they ſeeke to reconcile any to their mother the Church of Rome, they take them ſworne vpon the ſacrament of the altar, that they ſhall euer after cleaue faſt to tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſyna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gogue, &amp; renounce all our doctrine &amp; church aſſemblies. And before they haue thus made them their owne, and fettered their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with a vowe they doe not open their pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of Romiſh wares vnto them. They beginn with perſwaſions and end with inſtructions. But the trueth, ſaith Tertullian, perſwadeth by inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, inſtructeth not by perſwaſion.<note place="margin">ibidem. Veritas docen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perſuadet, non ſuadendo doc.</note> And doubtleſſe trueth is euer ſtrong and will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with as many as God hath ordained to eternall life. The Lords ſheepe may ſtray a time: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at laſt the cheife ſheapheard that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth 99 in the wildernes and goeth to ſeeke what is loſt, will finde them in mercy, and ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully bring them to his folde, and to the reſt that ſtraied not as they did. Nowe touching your caſe, good mother conſider well in your ſelfe this one thing; whether any vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way lavvfully giue me an oath, or I lavvfully take an oath either to doe vvhat God flatly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6779:45"/>forbiddeth me, or to leaue vndone what God flatly commandeth me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>No ſure: I am fully reſolued of that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Then muſt I conſider not onely that I haue ſworne, but to what I haue ſworne, and if I finde that vnlawfull, you ſee my oath may not binde me againſt the Lord. Nowe we boldly avowe, as you haue heard, and euer ſo did we avowe, that if any parcel of our chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith wherevnto we perſwade be not that which God in his word hath commanded, and forbidden the contrary, we will renounce it. Therefore I muſt weigh the doctrine as well as my vow or oath, and if the doctrine be true that I haue ſworn againſt, and that falſe which I haue ſworne to keepe, you haue confeſſed that you thinke this oath wicked and not to be kept.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, I cannot ſay otherwiſe, for my conſcience telleth me it is ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Howe then is it that many thus entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led neuer goe about to conſider the matter, but altogether ſticke to their oath, and thinke with themſelues: I haue ſworne; therefore I may not chaunge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I know it to be true: and I ſee it is a falt: for ſurely no oath ought to force me either to euill or from good concerning the loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6779:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>or ſauing of my ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Your true opinion mother, in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, may be confirmed by examples out of gods booke. Iephtha you know made a raſh vowe,<note place="margin">Iud. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which is in the nature of an oath, to offer to God what firſt met him out of his houſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he returned home, and had gotten the victory againſt his enemies. His own daughter mette him firſt. Did he well to kill her? What if a dogge or a ſwine had met him, beeing things that God would not abide to be vſed in ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, ſhould his oath haue tyed him directly to doe that which god abhorred? if not thoſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not his childe, if obedience be better then ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of things lawefull, how much more then ſacrifice of ſuch crueltie and vnnaturall blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe? Iephta therefore is condemned and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal be for this wicked keeping of his vow. Herod made a promiſe to his dancing daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you know the ſtory: did he well to keepe that oath? Iudge in your conſcience how God liked that fact. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ext ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Herod was ſorry whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he heard her petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet for his oaths ſake he ſent and beheaded Iohn Baptiſt in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. O bloodie oath and ſinfull keeping of it. His co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience whipped him whilſt he liued for it, and made him thinke when he heard of Chriſt that Iohn was riſen againe whome he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6779:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>had beheaded. In the Acts of the Apoſtles cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Iewes more then fortie men bound the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with an oath that they would neither eat nor drinke till they had ſlaine Paule.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And muſt they needes either kill that bleſſed Apoſtle, or pine themſelues to death by refuſing food, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had ſworne? God forbidde. I aſſure my ſelfe you like better of the Apoſtles words, we muſt obey God rather then men: And god ſaith <hi>thou ſhalt do no murther.</hi> Gehezy in the booke of the kings ſware <hi>that he vvould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe after Naaman, and take ſomwhat of him.</hi> he kept that vnlawfull oath, and by the feareful plague that fel vpon him you may ſee and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your ſelfe howe it pleaſed God; Dauid a man worthie following tooke another courſe, as we reade in his ſtorie: when he had ſworne to kill Naball, and not to leaue a man of his houſe to looke vppon a wall, yet meeting with his wife Abigail by the way, and admoniſhed by her of ſo hard a courſe, he changed his minde, bleſſed God that had ſent her as a mean to ſaue him from ſhedding blood, and thought ſo wel of the woman, that after the death of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, he married her. Had Dauid ſaid, as decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſoules nowe a daies doe, I haue ſworn, and I muſt keepe mine oath, greatly had he ſinned againſt the Lord to his owne hurt. This is an
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6779:46"/>example chronicled vp of God in his owne booke, to be followed of all thoſe that feare him. An oath is ordained of God to ende ſtrife beeing lawfully taken, and to ſtrengthen truth,<note place="margin">Firma mentu veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on vinculum ini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quitatis,</note> but in no caſe to be <hi>vniculum iniquitatis, a bond to tie vs to iniquity.</hi> Moſt worthily ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwered Ageſilaus, when one ſaid, <hi>Thou haſt promiſea, Yea, if it be iuſt,</hi> ſaith he, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>loquutus ſum, non promiſi, I ſpake, but it vvas no promiſe,</hi> meaning that no promiſe ſhould be vrged beyond right. May we thinke that he by the light he had, would haue ſtood vpon a wicked oath? no no aſſuredly: <hi>Non prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabit fides quod exhibuit infidelitas, Faith may not performe vhat vvant of faith vnlawfully ſvvare and vowed.</hi> By the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law (which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Popes owne law) who ſware in his heat, was to be enioined pennance, becauſe <hi>calor ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiae non excuſat à toto, ſed à tanto, The heate of anger excuſeth not from all fault, but from ſo great a fault:</hi> neither are they to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted periured, who can ſhewe impoſsibilitie, or impietie in their performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. your hart meant not to ſweare to euill: it then it prooue euil, and ſo you change, the fault is in the matter not in you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhall ſuch do then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Surely chooſe rather to aske god barrely
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6779:47"/>mercy for a raſh and ignorant oath, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the ſame to adde ſinne vnto ſinne, yea a farre greater to a leſſer; for in preſumption to offend is the next conſin to the ſin againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ghoſt. Beware that ſaying in the Pſalm.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>They encourage themſelues in miſcheife,</hi> that is, are bold and hardie to take heart to do euill, after they are tolde of it and knowe that it is euill. Remember that in Gods law, there was a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice appointed to make an attonement for one that had ſworne to doe euill.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vit. 5. ſal. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> A ſacrifice alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth now, euen a troubled ſpirit, ſorrowful for mine vnaduiſed oath, mine vnlawfull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wicked oath againſt my God, againſt my prince, againſt my country to obey a forrainer, a ſtraunger whome I neuer ſaw, neuer am like to ſee, againſt mine own ſoules health, and to my endleſſe woe. O Lord, O Lord, a broken &amp; contrit heart thou ſhalt neuer deſpiſe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtrengthen thy poore creature, to turne vnto thee, and rather to lament one ſinne, then ſtill ſtill to ſin, and ſo by an imagination of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy to periſh eternally for their contumacy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Amen, ſonne amen, for ſure it is plaine that you haue ſaide to this point, and ſweet is trueth when one doth taſt it. But the worlde is ſo full of prittle prattle when a man turneth that one will be aſhamed to heare their ſpeech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome are hindred euen thus.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:6779:47"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>No queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mother, but Satan vſeth this amongeſt other meanes to keepe ſome backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth,<note place="margin">The pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pratle of the world keepe ſome from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> truth.</note> &amp; it is a known weaknes in our nature to ſhrinke at the talk of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is old, a wonder laſteth but 9. nights: folly will die, and trueth get ſtrength: god is in this chaunge, and it cannot doe ill.<note place="margin">Ang. de. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 5. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> To haue it verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of vs which Chriſt ſpake of his enemies, is a fearefull thing, namely, that they loued the praiſe of men more then the praiſe of God The bleſſed Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Goe I about to pleaſe men? ſurely If I ſhould doe ſo, I were not the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt.</hi> And why? Our Sauiour Chriſts words giue one reaſon,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> becauſe ſuch cannot be tru beleeuers. <hi>For how can they beleeue</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which receiue honour one of another, and ſeeke not the honour vvhich commeth of God alone?</hi> There is extant in print a little booke contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the recantations of William Tedder and Anthony Tyrrel ſometime two ſeminarie prieſts of the Engliſh colledge in Rome, as they were ſeuerally pronounced by them at Pauls croſſe in the yere 1588. wherein they both ſhew what letted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their times to be reformed. &amp; firſt W. Ted. ſaith, one great cauſe was this we now ſpeak of, the feare of wordly ſhame &amp; temporall diſcredit: but ſaith he. I did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider then, or I cared not for that ſentence
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6779:48"/>of our ſauiour. <hi>Every one that confeſſeth me before men, him vvill I confeſſe alſo before my father vvhich is in heauen,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 10.</note> and whoſoeuer ſhall be aſhamed of me and of my words, in this adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and a ſinfull nation the ſonne of man ſhall be aſhamed of him,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> when he commeth in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his father with his angells.</hi> This was the cauſe that made me take a prepoſterous way turning all things to mine owne credit, when I ſhould haue turned them to the glory of God, according to our Sauiours councell: <hi>ſeeke firſt the kingdome of God &amp;c.</hi> So thinking to get credit by mine obſtinacy,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> did looſe, ſaith he, the fauour of God, the loue of my ſoueraigne, and the good will of all true ſubiects. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe ſaith he, was the tickling of vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorie, and this I am ſure doth hold moſt of the contrarie ſide in their peruerſe obſtinacy, howeſoeuer they bragge that they ſeeke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by their dealings but the glorie of God. I thought it a goodly thing and worthie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to defend an euill cauſe by proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons, yet I know it was a hard thing for Anaxagoras to prooue that ſnow was blacke or incke white, and for me to prooue light to be darkeneſſe, and darkenes light. Thus ſpake this Tedder, and ſpared not himſelfe in that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen place. The other Anthonie Tyrrell to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6779:48"/>ſame effect vſed theſe wordes: Here, ſaith he I muſt confeſſe to the great honour of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, that I haue had many and vehement temptations to hinder me from this action of repentance, but they beeing worldly and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with the ſword of Gods ſpirit I haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne them and cut them in peeces, One was this, the ſhame of the world, if I ſhould turne: againſt which I haue learned nowe to ſay, <hi>Melius est confunài in hoc ſeculo, quàm in futuro. Better it is to be confounded in this vvorlde, then in the vvorld to come:</hi> &amp; againſt pride and hautineſſe of minde, which did alſo trouble me, I haue learned to ſay with Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, <hi>Melior eſt in malis factis humilis confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio, quam in bonis ſuperba gloriatio, Better it is vvhen a man hath done evill, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly to confeſſe his fault, then proudly to vaunt of his well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> and rather had I with the penitent publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can confeſſe my ſelfe an open ſinner, then with the proude Phariſee to prooue my ſelfe an open liar. Thus doe you ſee, good mother, the hindrance which you obiect of talke and ſpeech of the world in theſe two men, both ſchollers and both prieſts, and yet howe God in mercy gaue them the vpper hand ouer ſuch weakeneſſe. You knowe Nicodemus his caſe. He liked of Chriſt, and very willing he was to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6779:49"/>be his diſciple, but he came by night, that hee might not looſe his credit of the world: we all confeſſe it a weakneſſe in him. And ſo certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is it to feare the tongues of men that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued as we were before god gaue vs light. Neuer had Prophet, Apoſtle, Martyr, or childe of God done any duty if they had hanged vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens tongues, and more regarded the vaine breath of their tauntes, which haue but a time and vaniſh as ſmoake, rather then that trueth and that God which is for euer. It was well ſaid of one, <hi>Qui conſcientias ſuas in alienis la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biis poſuerunt, modò magni, modò parui, modo nulli ſunt. They that hange their conſciences on other mens lipps, ſometimes are great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times litle, ſometimes no body:</hi> ſo vile and vaine is this courſe.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. l. 14.</note> Polycletus (ſaith Aelian) made two pictures, one after the fancy and correction of euery one that found any fault, another after his owne true skill and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: But O the difference of theſe tvvo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures! Diogenes is ſaid vpon an extreame colde day to haue ſtood in the water to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his body, and many looking vpon him had pittie on him, but at laſt Plato ſeeing vvhat vvas done, and vviſely perceiuing the mans vanity, ſaid, Maſters if you pitty him indeede, goe you avvay from him, meaning that vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:6779:49"/>they were gone, of whom he vainly hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for praiſe, he would come roundly out, and to the fire. Such a groſſe folly is it to ſeeke to pleaſe men and to be highly eſteemed of men for any thing, eſpecially for errour and miſ-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This is as S. Hierom ſaith, to be <hi>gloriae ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal &amp; popularis rumoris venale mancipium:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 26.</note> The vaſſall of vaine-glorie, and the ſold ſlave of popular praiſe.</hi> The winde hoiſteth vp the light duſt and ſcattereth all abroad: ſo doth the hanging too much on mens lips hurt many a man and woman well diſpoſed, and diſperſe the good motions of their minde. Therefore wiſe was that deuiſe of Philippe king of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,<note place="margin">Aelian. l. 12.</note> who to make a vaine Phiſitian delighted with mens praiſes too much to ſee his errour, invited him amongeſt many moe to a royall feaſt, and placing him at a boord by himſelfe, when all the reſt had great ſtore of meate, he had onely ſweete fumes and ſmokes made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and ſo roſe with an hungrie belly. I will ende with that ſpeech which like a dart me thinkes pierceth when it is ſpoken or read with reuerence and due meditation. <hi>Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem habent; verely, verely, I ſay vnto you they haue their reward. Men they would pleaſe, and praiſe they vvould haue, it is their ende, and they haue it,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour: but they had
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6779:50"/>better be without it, for they looſe the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Lord, and procure themſelues euerlaſting ſhame. Were the report good, or were the report euill, Paul did his duty in that which was good and had a bleſſed end.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, &amp; malam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt confeſſe ſonne, you are in the right, if fraile fleſh would be ruled. But what ſay you when a man or woman, haue beene long of this minde,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> change on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuddaine is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d, but delay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gerous.</note> can they change vpon the ſuddaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>O mother, what ſhould I ſay? your ſelfe be iudge and anſwer your ſelfe. Did euer any whome we reade of in the ſcripture, feeling the piercing power of Gods ſpirit ſmiting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rocke of their hidden hearts within, take time with the Lord, and ſay they would yeelde after three moneths, or ſixe moneths, &amp;c No, no, immediatly thoſe happy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that were pricked in their hearts at <hi>S.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſermon cried out:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we doe?</hi> Immediatly the Eunuch, the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, the happie woman Lydia, Cornelius and all the reſt ſpoken of in ſcripture were refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 16.</note> They ſtaied not an houre houering and hammering,<note place="margin">z. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 16.</note> looking backe to Sodome with Lots wife, or to Egypt with the Iewes; but ioifully embraced the trueth without delay. Surely they are ſet downe as holy examples for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6779:50"/>vs to followe. To day, to day, is the voice of God: and to morrow, to morrow is the voice of Satan. Herein doth ſinne and Satan deceiue vs, that they will haue to day, and god muſt haue to morrowe. <hi>Now, nowe is the accepted time,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>&amp; illud nunc, nullum ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bet craſtinum,</hi> ſaith the godly father Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, <hi>That now hath no morrow.</hi> All Satans fetch (ſaith another) is to make vs deferre, and ſo by deferring to looſe vtterly Gods offered mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; <hi>Qui non eſt hodie, cras minùs aptus erit, He that is not fit to day will certenly be more vnfit to morrow: Quot vicibus, tot vinculis,</hi> ſaith Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie of continuance in any euil: the longer we continue in it, the ſtiffer we ſhall be and the more obſtinate. And of doing good its truely ſaid of another, <hi>Quanto magis differtur, tanto difficiliùs redditur, vel propter peccati conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem, vel propter maiorem dei offenſionem: The longer it is deferred, the harder it is to performe, either in respect of the ſtrength of ſinne through cuſtome, or the offence of god in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by ſo deferring. Make no longer tarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſaieth the wiſe Siracides, <hi>tu turne vnto the Lord, neither put it off from day to day: for ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſhall the wrath of the Lorde breake forth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and in thy ſecurity thou ſhalt be deſtroyed, and thou ſhalt periſh in the time of vengeance. The
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6779:51"/>Lord vvill giue thee a penny</hi> (ſaith S. Auſten) <hi>though thou come but at the eleuenth hovvre, but yet he hath not promiſed thee to live to the ſecond hovvre:</hi> noting the vncertainty of our life not to be preſumed vpon, one moment of an howre: <hi>tu ergò quò quando vocaris, veni: thou therefore</hi> ſaith he, <hi>come vvhither thou art called, and vvhen thou art called,</hi> come, come, without any longer ſtay, or any moe ifs and ands, or conſultations with fleſh and blood. It is thy God that calleth, who allowed not him to goe bury his father, or to ſalute his friendes that ſought that delay, but required forthwith, Follow thou me: Zacheus when the Lord ſaid vnto him, <hi>come dovvne for I will dine with thee,</hi> came dovvne haſtely and receiued him ioyfully, which God in mercy make vs euer to doe: Whoſe image and ſuperſcription is vpon you, euen vpon your bodie, and vpon your ſoule? is it not Gods? ô giue then vnto God that which is Gods, your owne ſelfe to your own ſweete and good God, and ſee the comfort of it: Lord ſtrengthen, Lord help for thy ſonnes ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Amen, ſonne, and god giue ſatisfaction in our conſciences euer to chooſe what is right in his eyes. For conſcience is truely called the bird in my breaſt that would not be troubled.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:6779:51"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>True ſatisfaction of conſcience, mother, is a good thing, and euer to be laboured for. But I beſeech you marke howe greatly this word is abuſed, when fancy and will are called conſcience. Now a daies let it be asked of any recuſant (as we call them) why he or ſhee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to Church, the common anſwere is, forſooth my conſcience will not let me; or, It is my conſcience &amp;c, as though euery toy that I take in my head were by and by conſcience. Aske them further, why their conſcience will not let them; either they cannot or will not anſwere, but thinke they haue ſaid enough when they haue named once the word Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Alas, we knowe that true conſcience hath a ground and reaſon out of Gods word: as when I ſay my conſcience will not ſuffer me to kill a man, and you aske me why? I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily anſwere, becauſe it is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> and ſo in all other matters forbidden &amp; diſalowed by almightie God: which if they could doe either in this matter of comming to Church, or in any other point of obedience commanded by her Maieſtie and the lawe of this land, then might they talke of conſcience, and make ſcruple with authoritie, becauſe we muſt obey God rather then man. But this beeing not ſo foraſmuch as nothing is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6779:52"/>inioyned them that is contrarie to the worde, therefore this conſcience of theirs is but fancy, wilfull obſtinacy, and diſobedience, which the Lord will puniſh: for we are plainely taught that euerie ſoule ought to be ſubiect to the higher powers: there is no power but of God:<note place="margin">m. 13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the powers that be are ordained of God and they that reſiſt ſhall receiue to themſelues damnation, all beeing bound to be ſubiect not for feare of wrath onely, but alſo for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake. For humane lawes enacted of things that be good in themſelues, that is, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God, properly are not humane but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine lawes, and therefore binde conſcience not becauſe they were enacted by man, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were firſt made by God, men bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more but inſtruments and miniſters in his name to reviue, renewe, and put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuch precepts and lawes as preſcribe the worſhip of God, ſtanding in the practiſe of true religion and vertue: and the man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that breaks ſuch lawes ſinneth two waies: firſt becauſe he breakes that which in nature and conſcience is the lawe of God; ſecondly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in diſobeying his lawfull magiſtrate, he diſobeyeth the generall commandement of God touching magiſtrats.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>You wil haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience then euer grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6779:52"/>vpon Gods word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Yf it be a right conſcience, I ſay it muſt needes be ſo. For it is called <hi>Conſcientia, quaſi cum ſcientiâ</hi> (or as ſome thinke) <hi>quaſicordis ſcientia, as if you ſhould ſay with ſcience and knowledge, or the knowledge of the heart.</hi> Now true knowledge what pleaſeth or diſpleaſeth God, muſt needes be out of his word, becauſe therein onely his will is manifeſted vnto vs A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the actions of the conſcience (ſaith the Apoſtle) are in accuſing and excuſing which needes muſt haue relation to the word. For how can conſcience iuſtly accuſe me, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the thing I doe is condemned of God, or howe can it excuſe me, but becauſe my deedes by gods worde, which is his will, are iuſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Conſcience therefore without direction of gods word cannot giue true iudgement ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to iuſtification or condemnation. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therefore is done with an erroneous conſcience we ſee plainely is ſinne: for euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth euill, though conſcience ſay the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary a thouſand times: and ſo doth good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine good. As if a man come into an houſe in the darke, where many thinges are out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which yet for the darkeneſſe he ſeeth not to be ſo, are they not therfore out of order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſeeth them not? The like may be ſaide
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6779:53"/>on the other ſide where all things are paſsing well, and yet he ſeeth it not. Conſcience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a guid to me, and the word of God a guide to my conſcience: which if it were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and grounded in our hearts, o how would we tremble to be ſo ignorant of Gods word, as often we are, and to doe as we doe, and ſay as we ſay. This makes vs to runne headlong with good intents, whereas no good intention is ſufficient to make any worke good vnleſſe withal conſcience approoue my action, which it can neuer rightly doe, but by giuing iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God approoueth it. This makes vs bolde to worſhip God with mans inuentions,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay. 29.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ark. 7.7.</note> not conſidering that ſuch deuiſes are meere ſinnes, becauſe conſcience cannot ſay of them according to her rule, that they pleaſe God. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally as one ſaith with a godly deſire to awake vs. This maketh mans life flowe euen with a ſea of offences againſt God, men commonly thinking that if they keepe themſelues from periury, blaſphemy, murder, theft, whordome, all is well with them. But the trueth is, ſo long as they liue in ignorance, they want true and right direction out of Gods word: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their beſt actions are ſinnes, euen their ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking, their ſleeping and waking, their buying and ſelling, their ſpeech and ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6779:53"/>yea their praying &amp; ſeruing of God. For they doe theſe actions either of cuſtome or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or neceſsity, as beaſts doe, and not of faith, becauſe they knowe not gods will touching things to be done or left vndone. Wherefore the due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration hereof ſhould make euery man moſt carefull to ſeeke for knowlede of Gods word and daily to increaſe in it, that he may in all his affaires haue gods lawes to be the men of his councell, that he may giue heede to them as to a lantarne vnto his feete; and a light vnto his pathes. So ſhall conſcience be a ſure guide, and he reforme himſelfe by true obedience both to God and man. Otherwiſe as I haue ſaide, what we call conſcience, is but a fancie, a conceit, and a falſe erroneous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, ſuch as if we ſtill will follow againſt God, againſt prince, againſt countrie, and all that euer any gouernours or friendes can ſay vnto vs: the daie will come when wee ſhall feele with woe the puniſhment of ſuch obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, and true conſcience ſhall witneſſe the want of conſcience in ſo proudly diſobeying all good perſwaſions, which God forbid in his great mercy, and turne our hearts in time vnto his trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But I take it there is a plaine ſcripture, that who ſo doth a thing which in his heart he
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6779:54"/>thinketh he ſhould not doe, committeth dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinne, becauſe he doth againſt his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or againſt his owne pretenſed know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good mother, the ſcripture you mean (as I conceiue) is written in the 14 chapter of the Epiſtle to the Romans, where the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>He that doubteth, is condemned if he eate becauſe he eateth not of faith: and what ſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne.</hi> Which place lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle helpeth any popiſh ignorance or ſtubburne wilfullneſſe, but is greatly by Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes abuſed and wreſted, as other ſcriptures to ſerue for their way wardneſſe. Concerning which text, thus haue our men truely and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily anſwered long agoe and often: firſt that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh there of a particular and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine matter, papiſts applying theſe wordes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally to whatſoeuer they doe contrary to their erroneous conſcience or pretenſed kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge, 2. that the particular matter which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of is a thing indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Papiſts apply the wordes to things ſimply good, and ſimply euill, ſaying the former may be left vndone if my erring conſcience be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, the later done without ſinne, if my pretenſed knowledge lead me to it. 3. That the things which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of, were
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6779:54"/>ſuch as God himſelfe was author of in his lawe, as diſtinction of meate and daies, which whilſt the Iewes wonne to the Goſpel did in thoſe daies retaine, though they did it ignorantly, not knowing the libertie of the Goſpell, yet till they might be fully perſwaded therein by faith, which is grounded on doctrine and on the word, they were bound to keepe by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God himſelfe. 4. That the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and end of the Apoſtles bearing is not to nouriſh errour, or to harden ſuch an one in his opinion and doing, but by patience to drawe him to trueth in the ende, which manner of to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerance the Apoſtle calleth <hi>edification,</hi> verſ. 19. and chap. 15.2. Laſtly the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not of Gentiles &amp; infidels, nor of ſtubburn Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but of a brother, a faithfull man, and one that hath receiued and embraced the profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell, but is weake through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſome one point pertaining to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an liberty in the outward vſe of Gods creatures wherein he is not throughly perſwaded of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed; of bearing with ſuch an one by thoſe whome God hath called to more plentifull knowledge of his heauenly trueth, ſpeaketh he. All which things duly conſidered, the true ſence of the place appeareth thus: namely that the faithfull for his particular regard beeing in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6779:55"/>doubt, or lacking the full perſwaſion of faith (which is giuen by meaſure, and hath his time of groweth and increaſing) cannot without danger, (and therefore ought not) attempt to do that wherein he is not already by the word of God and faith fully and throughly reſolued. But mark this double caution; firſt, that his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteining from the outward action be without danger of offence, and ſcandall &amp; ſecondly, that he ſtand not ſtiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly in his owne opinion, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe therein, but ready vpon further inſtruction and knowledge to grow forward and to profit, yea deſirous alſo of ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and whatſoeuer other meanes may help to the better informing of his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in that behalfe, whereby he may both clearely ſee the thing doubted of to the good, holy, and lawfull, &amp; do the ſame with all ſincerity &amp; faithfullnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But what if without da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of offending God and prince, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abſtaine from the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward action, and yet doubt in my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Your obedience beeing due, it leſſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to commit one fault then two, that is to doe what you ought though doubtingly, then both do doubt and diſobey. The doubting is a fault, the obedience is none. Amend what is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill by better inſtruction, withdraw not what is good and due by all right. <hi>He is condemned</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:6779:55"/>ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>if he eate, not becauſe he eteth but becauſe he eateth not of faith.</hi> In a lawefull action therefore it is not the deed which offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, but the doubting, that is, not the matter, but the manner: performe obedience with a ſingle heart and God in meane ſhall bleſſe it with true reſolution.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Doth not then an erroneous conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence binde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>It may be borne withall for a time in charitable regard of weakeneſſe, and in hope of better inſtruction, but God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde that it ſhould ſtill binde, and bee a couer or excuſe for wilfull, waywarde, and malitious diſobedience.<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 1. Tim. 4.</note> For then to bee giuen ouer to a ſtrong deluſion to beleeue lies is not ſuch a iudgement as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle maketh it, neither yet to haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience feared with an hotte iron.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.19</note> It is not right which the Apoſtle teacheth that vpon the putting away of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience their followeth any ſhipwracke of faith, or that the wicked haue their very mindes and conſciences defiled.<note place="margin">1. Tit. 1.</note> For if the colour of ſuch a conſcience binde, excuſe and ſaue harmeles, how is it defiled? can that which is defiled it ſelfe make cleane any action? But ô miſerable doctrine! that falſe reaſon
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:6779:56"/>ſhould be made a guide to will, and we bound to followe ſo blinde a guide. The very heathen philoſophers were not ſo madde. For they talke of <hi>recta ratio,</hi> and of <hi>mens ſana in corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſano, of right and true reaſon, and of a ſound minde in a ſounde body, &amp;c.</hi> A Iewe ſinneth mortally (ſay theſe Catholike teachers) if co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his pretenſed knowledge or againſt his erroneous conſcience he acknowledge in Trinitie Ieſus Chriſt the ſecond perſon, yea the Iewes had ſinned mortally if they had not cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified Chriſt according to their erring conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Againe to beleeue in Chriſt, if falſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon propound it as euill, is euill, yea to worſhip the deuill beeing deceiued by the ſame reaſon, is not onely not a ſinne, but a good worke. O Catholike doctrine! Then for the ſecond table; if a man leauing his wife, and going into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countrie, marry another, and after repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe would leaue her, affirming his former wife to be aliue, and the Church ſuffer him not, beeing ignorant of the trueth of that his aſſertion, although this latter marriage bee nought and the man conſequently an adulterer (Deare mother marke this ſtuffe) the woman being excuſed by ignorance, yet compelled by the diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Church, his obedience ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth him. This is groſſe and knowne adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:6779:56"/>excuſed by theſe holy Catholicks: falſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and erring conſcience ruleth this kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of darkeneſſe ſo ſhamefully If this be not liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniſme, what is? Alas why might not this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour be ſhewed in Queene Maries daies that an erring conſcience ſhould excuſe? Why were men and women then compelled to doe contrary to their conſciences, which at worſt muſt be granted to be erroneous conſciences. Nay ſee their partiality yet more: for if one of their prelats command what a mans erring co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſtardeth at, then they ſay ſuch a man ought to lay away that his conſcience and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his prelate. And why not when God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth ſhould a man doe the like? O blinde guides, what doctrine is this? if the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an inferiour officer or magiſtrate bind not when the ſuperiour as King or Emperour commandeth the contrary, how may an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring conſcience euer bind me againſt the Lord? Gods booke is ſo farre from allowing this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring conſcience, and this prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed knowledge, that it onely alloweth good, and ſuffereth not euill to be done, that good may come of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, I ſee more harſhneſſe in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine then I did before. But on the other ſide to compell and force any body by lawes and penalty, before the conſcience be fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:6779:57"/>is it not as harſh and hard to?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S</speaker>
               <p>VVhere there is an honeſt plaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to indeauour to be perſwaded and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, god forbidde but ſome time ſhould bee graunted. And I thinke it is ſo in all places. But propound the matter thus: whether a godly prince after a time giuen &amp; meanes graunted to be taught and inſtructed, and after al gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; patience vſed, his ſubjects refuſing to be taught, and contemning that gratious &amp; great fauour, continuing ſtill perve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly and obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Idolatrie, and ſuperſtition, whether I ſay, then by lawes and puniſhments to compel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the true worſhip of God, be ſo harde and harſh? And then truth wil anſwer that it is not, but iuſt, godly, and fit. For not onely to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine publike peace is the ſword giuen, but alſo to ſee that God be ſerued according to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trieis cal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tum.</note> that is, both the tables are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, &amp; the breaches of both ought by him to be puniſhed, otherwiſe man ſhould bee regarded more then God, &amp; the leſſer duties more then the greater. In which holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duty hath not the magiſtrate god for his patterne, who after words of admonition giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his own elect &amp; deare children, if they take no place, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelleth as it were by croſſes &amp; rods of his fatherly loue to the bettering of their courſe &amp; leauing of euill? Yea is not our own
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:6779:57"/>practiſe ſo with our own children, if gentle ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition will not ſerue? wherevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaying ſpra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge; <hi>he that ſpareth the rod hateth the child.</hi> what ſhall we ſay to the Scriptures, that are as plaine for the warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this matter as we need to deſire: did not Nabuchodonoſor make a law that euery people, nation, and language, which ſpak any blaſphemy againſt the god of Sidrach &amp;c. ſhould be drawn in peeces,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.29.</note> &amp;. their houſes made a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>akes? Darius alſo made another decree chap 6. In the book of Chronicles Aſa deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Idolatry, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth his people to ſerue the true God,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 14.14</note> yea he ſweareth them, and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his mother for adulterie: whoſe erroneous conſcience was in all likelihood as ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as any Papiſts for his popery. In the book of Ezra we read that the king of Perſia made a decree that the Iewes ſhould build their temple, that they ſhould haue all things neceſſarie for their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that they might offer ſweet odours vnto the God of heauen, &amp; pray for the kings life, &amp; the life of his ſonns. Alſo he made another law that whoſoeuer ſhould alter that ſentence,<note place="margin">a penal ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the wood ſhould be pulled down from his houſe and ſet vp, and he hanged thereon, &amp; his houſe made a dunghil for this.<note place="margin">Ezra. 6.11.</note> And the god that hath cauſed his name to dwell their (ſaith that lawe) deſtroy all kings and people that put their hand to alter and deſtroy this houſe of God
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:6779:58"/>which is in Hieruſalem: Idarius haue made a decree, let it be done with ſpeede. After againe (which I pray you good mother to marke) authority is giuen to ſet iudges and arbiters which may iudge all the people that is beyond the riuer,<note place="margin">p. 7.25.</note> euen al that knowe the lawe of God: and to teach all that know it not: and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will not obey the law of God &amp; the kings lawe (ſaith that ſtatute) let him haue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t without delay: whether it be vnto death or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, to confiſcation of goodes or to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. What lawe did euer any prince make more plaine without any regard to a pretended conſcience wanting true grounde out of the law of god? For if that might either then or nowe be allowed, what lawe coulde holde, againſt which he that liſt not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, would not obiect his erroneous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? VVhat gouernment could any prince in the world ſettle and eſtabliſh? Away there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with this idle dreame of a pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and marke how neuer in any gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it was regarded after waies and meanes vſed for the reformation of it, but euer ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the penaltie of the lawe, beeing indeede an obſtinacy both againſt god and prince, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy puniſhment. In the newe teſtament is it not ſaide,<note place="margin">Luk. 14.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Goe into the high vvaies anà compell
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:6779:58"/>to come in that my houſe my be full.</hi> I forgotte to remember you of that lawe and penall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made by the king of Ninive,<note place="margin">Ionah. 3.</note> which was ſo well liked of god: but you may now thinke of it, and adde it to the reſt of the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If we looke at practiſe, Polonia, Ruſsia, Lituania were forced at the commaundement of their rulers to forſake their auntient Idols,<note place="margin">Munſt. Coſm. 4. p. 894.902. L. 3. p. 719.74</note> and to receiue baptiſme. Good princes alſo maintained long and ſharpe warres to compell the Saxons and Vandals to the faith, &amp;c. The lawes of this realme [bleſſed be god] force to nothing but what is directly prooued in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And the conſtraint is not outragious with fire and ſword, but tempered with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that is, free from loſſe of life and limme, ſuch as the true Church of god neuer diſliked and Chriſtian princes alwaies vſed with great and good ſucceſſe. It is tempered alſo with good inſtruction to forſake error, wherewith Chriſt is diſhonoured and his trueth defaced. Romiſh Catholicks revenge the ſmalleſt contempt of their idle ceremonies with vnſufferable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Their prelats make it their occupation to perſecute to death all ſorts, ages, and Sexes which refuſe their ſchoole-tricks or dregges of their Clementines or decretalls Howe then can they finde fault with any due compulſion
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:6779:59"/>full of mercy and profit to all that be not mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly froward: yea all of them both Clergie and laity promiſed in baptiſme to hold this faith, therefore they may be compelled to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their promiſe. Gratian, Theodoſius, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadius, Honorius, and other Chriſtian princes with conuenient ſharpnes of poſitiue lawes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merced, baniſhed, and diuerſly puniſhed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes. And theſe coactions when the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts railed on them with open mouth, S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin defended and commended, writing to Vincentius thus. <hi>Thinkeſt thou</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that no man ought to the forced vnto righteouſnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piſt. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou readeſt that the maſter ſaid to his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts compeſt them to come in? and alſo that Paul was forced by loſſe of his eies, a greater puniſhment then loſſe of landes and goodes.</hi> Mark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt here firſt compelling, after teaching: ſtriking; then comforting. Let them not miſlike that they are forced but examine whereto they are forced. How doe kings (ſaith he) ſerue the Lord in feare but when they forbid and puniſh with religious ſeuerity thoſe things that are done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the commandement of God, as Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah did by deſtroying the groaues and temples built againſt the precepts of God, as did Ioſiah the king of Niniveh, Nabuchodonoſor, &amp;c. S. Ambroſe ſaith, <hi>Quoniam futurum iudicium
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:6779:59"/>Deus statuit, &amp; nullum perire vult, hoc in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo rectores ordinauit, vt terrore interpoſito om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus velut paedagogi ſint,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">in epiſt. ad. Rom. c. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>ne in paenam incida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t futuri iudicei. For aſmuch as God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a future and finall iudgement in the vvorld to come, and vvould not that any ſhould periſh, he hath ordained rulers in this preſent worlde, to be as it were ſchoolemaſters to all to keepe them through terrour that they incurre not the penaltie of the iudgement to come.</hi> Thus we ſee ſcripture, reaſon, practiſe, fathers, all allowing compulſion of an erroneous conſcience or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſed knowledge, which ſurely is enough to any moderate mind deſiring ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in true ſimplicitie, and not making couers for vngodly obſtinacie in ſubtile hypocriſy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne your anſweres are ſo reaſonable, that I will ſtill obiect, to heare your anſweres. What if I ſay God hath made vs free, therefore there is no reaſon any ſhould be compelled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Then will I anſwere (Good Mother) that euen our firſt parentes, who had freewill, had alſo both a lawe giuen them of God, and a penaltie added to the ſame if they ſhould tranſgreſſe it: much more now then may the like be done, when we haue both loſte our ſelues and our freewill
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:6779:60"/>(to vſe the wordes of S. Auſtin:) By no lawe is the will compelled, for that ſtill is either free or it looſeth his name of will. But men according to their bodies may be forced as well to keepe the commandements of the firſt table concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dutie to God, as the commandements of the ſecond table concerning dutie to men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>But againe I vvill ſay, this maketh men hypocrites, when outwardly they doe that which in their hearts they miſlike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>And againe I anſwere, that the drift of the magiſtrate is not to make them hypocrits, but by theſe meanes to drawe them willingly to doe that which thy are enioyned. And if it be not ſo, that is their fault, not the magiſtrates. So did God with Ionas, Paul, and others. So ſaith <hi>S</hi> Auguſtin of his owne cirtie fallen to Donatiſme,<note place="margin">ug. contr. auden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. l. 2. c. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>that by outvvard lavves they were brought to invvard knovvledge,</hi> and ſo he ſaw the benefit of this courſe, that the ſword ſhould raigne with the word, although at firſt he ſaith <hi>it vvas his opinion that none ſhould be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before he vvere perſwaded.</hi> And S Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſaith, <hi>Multi ſunt qui cùm virtutem pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm reſpectu magiſtratus exercuerunt, poſted etiam illam propter Dei timorem amplectun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">a Spiſt. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Many men vvhereas at firſt they be haue themſelues vertuouſly in regard of the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:6779:60"/>and for feare of puniſhment, afterwarde doe it gladly, euen for feare of God and in reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of his maieſtie.</hi> VVe ſee the iudgement of this holy father: that compulſion by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is neceſſarie and profitable, though at firſt it procure but externall obedience, and his reaſon which followeth is very good, <hi>Craſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res enim</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non adeo futura tangunt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que praeſentia:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>for carnall men are not ſo much touched vvith future as preſent thinges:</hi> that is (as I vnderſtand him) the torments of hell in the world to come doe not ſo much preuaile with them, as the puniſhment of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate preſently to be inflicted vpon them. And that Epiſtle of S. Auguſtin is moſt worthie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reading, his 48 epiſtle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Yet forced Religion pleaſeth not God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, it leſſe diſpleaſeth with one part to doe my duty, then with both partes to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. To come to Church with my bodies, where by Gods grace I may be caught, as S. Auguſtin was at S. Ambroſe his ſermon, then both with bodie and mind to diſobey not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prince but God. A part of my duty is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though it be not all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>The magiſtrate cannot giue faith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould not compell to faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>He doth not compell to faith, but to the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:6779:61"/>meanes whereby God vſeth to giue ſaith, namely, to hearing: for faith commeth by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and hearing by the word of God; which howe profitable it may be by Gods mercy, hath beene alreadie ſaid: and the words of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſhewe, when he ſaith, <hi>It is good for me that I haue beene in trouble, &amp;c.</hi> and the words of Ieremy, <hi>Castigaſti, &amp; Caſtigatus ſum, thou haſt chaſtned me, and I haue beene chaſtned.</hi> The words of Eſay, <hi>Vexatio dat intellectum Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and trouble vvorke vnderſtanding:</hi> The wordes of wiſe Salomon, <hi>Da ſapienti occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; ſapientior erit, giue a wiſe man occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and he vvill be vviſer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Why then did not Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pell any?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt was no magiſtrate: and we ſpeake of the Magiſtrate, and what he may doe by his office and authority giuen him by God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely Sonne, great is trueth, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth, I will trouble you no further in this matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>I will then deare mother, ſhut it vppe with S. Auguſtins wordes to the Donatiſts, <hi>Non bene facere legibus cogimini, ſed malè fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere prohibemini. Nam bene facere nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, niſi elegerit &amp;c. You are not compelled by lawes, to doe well, but you are forbidden and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to doe euill: For no man can doe well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:6779:61"/>he vvillingly doe it: Timor autem paenaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ciſi nondum habeat dilectionem bonae conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, ſaltem intra clauſtra cogitationis coercet malam cupiditatem: And the feare of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t although it haue not as yet the loue of good conſcience, yet at leaſt it reſtraineth euill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hidden cogitation Numquid quia mores optimi libertate voluntatis eliguntur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">contra Petil. l. 2. c. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>ideò mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res peſsimi non legis integritate puniuntur? Becauſe good manners are choſen by freedome of will, therefore are not ill manners puniſhed by integritie of lawe?</hi> In a worde, <hi>Aliter non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequimur vos niſi quemadmodum veritas per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequitur falſit atem: We perſecute you no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but as trueth perſecuteth falſhood, namely to ſaluation, not to deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Surely, your anſweres, I muſt confeſſe, are farre otherwiſe, then either I looked for at your handes, or thought coulde haue beene giuen in your cauſe. Wherefore I ſay againe we on our ſide are greatly wronged, when we are forbidden to read your bookes, or to conferre with you. But yet if ſome learned man were here to diſpute with you, happely he would contrarie this which to me ſeemeth plaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Surely mother, euen this alſo which you name is a good point be touched. For
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:6779:62"/>indeede it is an vſuall ſhift of men and women thus giuen to ſay. I cannot anſwere you, but if ſuch and ſuch were here they would: and, would God we might haue ſome diſputation, then ſhould wee ſee which part were better. Yea ſuch bragges are made by ſome learned of your ſide, to blinde the eyes of the people, as if either there neuer had bin triall of their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth this waie, or as if they alwaies had had the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand in diſputation; when God knoweth, and the world can witneſſe herein their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and great foiles, to the glorie of God and victory of his truth in the hearts of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes both men and vvomen. For confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof let me remember you of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputation at Berne in Heluetia, in king Henry the 8, his daies, which is thus publiſhed in Chro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicle to the worldes knowledge. There was in ☞the yeare of our Lord 1527. in the moneth of december order taken by the ſenate and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Berne, whoſe power amongſt all the Switzers chiefly excelleth in regard of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of religion that then was and ſtill more &amp; more increaſeth, that there ſhould be a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like diſputation in that cittie, and to that ende they ſent forth writings of the ſame, and called thither all the Biſhops bordering neere about them, as the biſhop of Conſtance, Baſil, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dune,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:6779:62"/>Lauſanna, warning them to come both themſelues and to bring with them their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, or els to looſe all ſuch profeſsions as they had lying within the boundes of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct. They alſo appointed learned men amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them, preachers of the Goſpell to be readie to diſpute againſt all commers in defence of their doctrine, preſcribing the diſputation to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided onely by the authority of the olde and newe teſtament. They graunted ſafe conduct to all that would come. They appointed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that all things ſhould be done modeſtly without iniurie and brawling words, and that euery one ſhould haue leaue to ſpeake his minde freely, and with ſuch deliberation that euerie mans ſaying might be receiued by the notarie and penned. And to the end men might come thither better prepared, they cauſed their miniſters to publiſh ſuch queſtions as they ſhould diſpute on before hand in writing, that euery man might ſtudie to ſay what he coulde againſt them, and they were tenne in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The true Church riſeth out of Gods worde, continueth in the ſame, and heareth the voice of none other.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The true Church maketh no lawes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:6779:63"/>
                     <item>3. <hi>Traditions binde not, but as firre as they are agreeable to the written word.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Chriſt onely hath ſatisfied for the ſinnes of the vvorld, and therefore if any make any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waie, the ſame denieth Chriſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. <hi>The body and blood of Chriſt cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued really and corporally by the teſtimony of ſcripture.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>There is no place of purging after this ☞life, and therfore all dirges, prayers, ceremonies, lampes, tapers, &amp;c. bestowed for the dead profitte nothing.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Chriſt onely is to be prayed vnto as the mediator of mankind to God the father.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. <hi>The maſſe is wicked and derogatory to Chriſts ſacrifice offered for vs.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>9. <hi>Images ought not to be ſet vp in Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and praied vnto.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>10. <hi>Marriage is allowed by God vnto all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Theſe things I ſay, thus agreed vpon before hand were ſent abroad to al places, and the day appointed the 7, of Ianuarie for the diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to beginne. At which day (nowe ſee the courage of Catholicks) not one of the biſhops before named came: neuertheleſſe the citty of Baſil, Zuricke, Schaſuſe, Abbacelle, Sangallium, Malluſia with the neighbours of Rhetia, alſo
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:6779:63"/>they of Strawsburge Vlmes, Ausburge, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daue, Conſtance and Iſue ſent thither their Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſſadours. The doctors of Berne began the diſputation, whereat were preſent Zuinglius, Oecolampadius, Bucerus, Capito, and Blaure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus with others. One the other ſide of them that were opponents, the chiefe was Conza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus and Tregerus, a frier Auguſtine, who no way able to prooue his cauſe out of the olde and newe teſtament, as was appointed and decreed at firſt, deſired that he might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Doctours: which the moderators refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to graunt, becauſe it was contrarie to the order appointed, he to his great ſhame, and to the preiudice of all his ſide departed out of the place and would diſpute no more. The diſputation endured 19. daies and in the ende by the greater part of that aſſembly the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes hadde the victorie, and the Papiſts the foile. And it was agreed vpon that the themes before mentioned were all true and agreeable to Gods holy worde, that they ſhoulde be ratified and proclaimed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to promiſe, and that maſſes, altars, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, &amp;c. ſhould in all places be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: So they were at Conſtance, Berne, and Geneva, they cauſing the day and yeare of this reformation from poperie to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:6779:64"/>to be ingrauen in a pillar with golden letters for a perpetuall memorie to all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. This was anno 1528. After the rumour of this diſputation, Reformation followed at Strawsburge, Baſil, and other places, to Gods great glorie, the comfort of his people, &amp; the true witneſsing to the world what ſtrength Romiſh Catholicks haue in diſputation, when they are deſired to keepe to the ſcriptures, which onely is the ground of trueth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. I may not repeat others at large, but bleſſed be God the like triall of them was made and the like foile giuen them at Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge, and Ravensburge, at Ausburge, at Spire at Wormes, at Pois, and here in England, at London, at Cambridge, at Oxford and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate houſes and conſiſtories of Biſhops often. That notable ſeruice of Beza, at Pois gone through the worlde, when the Cardinall of Lotharinge wiſhed that either Beza had beene dumme, or they his auditours and aduerſaries dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, will witneſſe for euer what pith popiſh falſhood hath had againſt Chriſtian trueth held and taught by proteſtants, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came to diſputation. Reade our owne Chronicles of the cowardly refuſall of the popiſh Biſhops to diſpute at the happy entrance of her Maieſty to the Crowne, howe alſo they behaued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:6779:64"/>in Queene Maries time, when one of them ſaid, <hi>vve had the word, but they had the ſword, &amp;c.</hi> Indeede, indeede, the ſword and the fire are their beſt arguments, and in blood they build whatſoeuer they build. Neuer, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, therefore let them boaſt of diſputation, or ſay they haue proſpered by it: for we neede not to feare them, God be bleſſed, nor they to bragge of any winning. There neuer wanted yet, neither euer ſhall want both learned and vnlearned on our ſide, whoſe ſpirits they ſhall not be able to reſiſt: writing, preaching, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they are the Goſpels weapons and waies to build by; Popery muſt take ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e other courſe as yet in all times they haue done which holde that plough. O that for further proofe of this point me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would be content without preiudice to read the Acts &amp; monuments of this our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue countrie, and Engliſh Church where we liue, marking with a minde deſirous of trueth what anſwers haue beene made by ſimple wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, maides, and girles vnto great Biſhops and Doctoures in cauſes of religion &amp; faith, to the great aſtoniſhment of their aduerſaries, &amp; the high glorie of God ſeene in their weakneſſe ſo ſtrengthened by him. But nothig can bee more grieuous to that Church then to graunt leaue to doe this, which ſurely bewrayeth they
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:6779:65"/>are afraide. Hence come their lies and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders invented againſt that book, which would full ſoone be diſcried of vs woulde we reade it. If any haue beene in Weſtminſter ball, at tharraignment of a miſdoer, we willingly heare him a whole day to tell vs the manner of it, what was obiected, what anſwered, what replyed, and what concluded: yet we will not read with our owne eies, hauing it ſo nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly penned for vs, the conventings of holy Chriſtian men and women before their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for matter of faith and ſaluation. We wil talke of diſputation, diſputations, and ô that men might be allowed to ſpeake freely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daunger of lawe what they are able: and when the time was for theirs to ſpeake what they would or coulde, and wee ſtoode at the barre in bolts and yron to anſwere their obiections and profound learning, we will not nowe reade what was then done &amp; ſaid on both ſides; Surely I will ſay of that booke what I wiſh tried, that after the ground of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures, it will yeelde the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. Men ſhall ſee men, women ſhall ſee women, age ſhall ſee age, and youth youth brought to the triall, howe they anſwered, howe they ſuffered, howe fleſh ſtartled,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:6779:65"/>howe the ſpirit conquered, and in a worde, howe God ſhewed his mercie and power infinite waies. If we finde they ſpeake well, we may embrace it, if otherwiſe leaue it. The Lord hath giuen vs wiſdome and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and of his grace alſo, I truſt to be able to diſcerne, if we would reade. O why ſhould our enemies hoodwincke vs ſo that we muſt neuer ſee but with their eies. If the charge of this book be to much for one, an whole pariſh might ioyne together and vſe it by turners, as leiſure ſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Sonne, I ſee you are ready for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way, and therefore hauing gone thus farre in triall of what you could ſay, and now being come to our iourneys ende, I will goe no further with you at this time, but reſerue the particular pointes of controuerſie till wee haue ſome fitte leiſure and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Good Mother, when and howe you pleaſe. But nowe ere we part I beſeech you let me ſpeake ſomething to you with out offence. I will not ſay much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Speake on, you ſhall doe more Then as yet you haue done, if you any way offend me.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:6779:66"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> religious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ite or a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ous child to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> mother.</note>My ſuite is then, moſt deare mother, with a melting heart of an humble childe, that you would vouchſafe to thinke of that which hath nowe beene ſpoken, as alſo of this feare, full courſe which you haue to long liked of in not comming to Church, not receiuing the ſacrament, not hearing Gods word, not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lawes of your dread and gratious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, and of your natiue countrie. It woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth your credit and eſtimation with the beſt, it hurteth my father, daunteth your children, blemiſheth your houſe, and wrongeth your friendes both neare &amp; deare moſt grieuouſly. But ô father I ſay againe, my heart burſteth and bleedeth to ſee howe he is eclipſed by it, in compariſon of others to whome he is no way inferiour, either in birth, in liuing, in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and experience, or in any gift in body or minde, neither hath his countrie that good from him, or he that good from his countrie that might be had if you were reformed. For how may he be thought ſo fit to rule others abroad, that cannot be obeied of his owne at home. His children therefore want him, his friends want him, his ſeruants want him, yea he himſelfe wanteth himſelfe many times to his griefe. Other things alſo I could name that better may be conceiued in your tender loue
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:6779:66"/>towardes him then by me expreſſed at this time. O mother pardon your owne fleſh in ſpeaking thus boldly to you, and knowe that it is but a part of your ſelfe that ſpeaketh to your ſelfe in tender louect dutie. When firſt my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matched with you, he hoped of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; countenance euery way to be increaſed to him both by your ſelfe and your excellent qualities wherewith God hath indued you, and by your friendes and houſe, to whome by this marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age he ſhould be vnited: not of any abaſhment and abatement in al theſe to him and his poore children the pledges of loue betwixt you. And thus might it be it you would, but alas, thus is it not, becauſe hitherto you would not. A fewe falſe charmers haue ſunke deeper into your heart with their deceits, then all your beſt friendes can with their faithful aduertiſements. And what is this els in you and others of your perſwaſion, but that which euer hath bin done by the olde ſerpent the head and guide of theſe charmers. In the Acts of the Apoſtles we read <hi>that the Iewes hating deadly the trueth of the Goſpell preached by the Apoſtles, and deſirous to vexe them for it, deuiſed this as the beſt means to ſtirre vp certaine honeſt and devout women againſt them, which women ſhould vvork with their friendes to expell ſuch preachers from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:6779:67"/>them.</hi> Nowe why women? but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Satan hath euer had his adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage againſt this weake veſſell? why devout women? but becavſe a religious minde meaning well, yet wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting knowledge is both quicklyer deceiued with ſhewe of religion, and hottelier purſueth what it once beginneth, doing more hurt in that falſe deuotion, then many others not ſo well thought of. And why honourable wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? but that might being added to blinde zeale both by power and example Satans cauſe might goe forwarde. <hi>Theſe charmers,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle againe, <hi>ſhall ſtill be creeping into houſes &amp; lead captiue ſimple women.</hi> By which often repeated name of women in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all good women are effectually warned to beware. Were there cauſe for you or any others thus to doe, it no way could ſtand with religion to diſwade you, and in my ſelfe to you Mother, it ſhould be a double ſinne, becauſe I am yours and aboue all wordly fauours ought to wiſh your eternall ſafetie before others: but the Lord knoweth, whoſe trueth is with vs, that there is no cauſe. And whatſoeuer by the power of all popiſh learning hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged as any cauſe, we haue anſwered ſoundly out of Gods booke, our anſweres ſtanding without reply vnto this day. Our
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:6779:67"/>ſeruice theeefore is lawfull, our praiers are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our meetings are Chriſtian: and no better way to be reſolued hereof, then part by part to examine them. So haue ſome done and beene reformed, wondering howe ſo great ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders could be raiſed where no cauſe is found. The authoritie alſo of lawefull gouernment commaundeth but lawefull things, increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the dutie to obey, and preſſeth with no ſmaller weight then damnation as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle flattely affirmeth if we reſiſt.<note place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Conceits may not take place, where ſuch euidence of trueth doth gainſay them. If I had a conceit or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that all meates would kill me, muſt I certainely die for want of meate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine my errour? The Galatians preſcribed themſelues amiſſe in ſome things, and the Apoſtle thought it a reaſon ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them, to tell them that ſuch a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was not the perſwaſion of him that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, meaning of God.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.8.</note> And the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures phraſe in the matter of perſwaſion is <hi>to adde through the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.24. 2. Theſ. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>I am perſvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through the Lord:</hi> which is worthie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Deare Mother, the Lords annointed ouer you, her ſacred Maieſtie, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this dutie, and there is no deuill of hell can prooue this charge vnlawefull.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:6779:68"/>Therefore by the bonde of a ſubiect true and faithfull you ought to obey. My father with ſighes and groanes of a troubled heart deſireth it, and therefore by the bonde of a wife louing and dutifull you ought to obey. And, which is the greateſt of all, the God that made you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth it to you and all his ſeruants: therfore by the bonde of a childe of God you ought to obey. The bondes are great, the duty is holy, the obedience is euerlaſting peace, comfort, &amp; life, the danger alſo is great to ſtriue to offend. And therefore happie is that heart that yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth betimes. If by reading their bookes this wound hath beene giuen you, then reade our anſweres and let God heale. They haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten no matter of moment theſe 40. yeares in our engliſh tongue, but fully and ſoundly is it anſwered to Gods glorie. Yea their new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein is their whole ſtrength heaped togither, is learnedly anſwered to the full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of any not deſperatly giuen ouer to his owne blindneſſe. In matter of lawe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the goodes of this world, you will heare contrarie opinions and chooſe with iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. In matter of phiſicke concerning your bodie, you will doe the like, &amp; beat out a trueth. Shall onely the ſoule be neglected and pinned on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſleeues? ô God forbidde. He hath
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:6779:68"/>promiſed that neuer deceiued, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo, <hi>Aske and you ſhall haue, ſeeke and you ſhall finde, knocke and it ſhall be opened vnto you.</hi> Thus ſhall we finde their great wickedneſſe in denying the ſcriptures to be read of them that haue ſoules to be ſaued as well as themſelues: their taking away the cuppe from the lay peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when Chriſts inſtitution was, <hi>Drinke ye all of this:</hi> their leauing the ſecond commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of their catechiſmes, becauſe it forbid deth Images, their multitude of bodily exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, when the ſcripture ſaith they profit little: their killing of princes, when the Lord ſaith. Touch not mine annointed, and Dauids heart ſmote him for cutting off but the lappe of Sauls garment, and to no worſe ende then to make him ſee his innocency, and his guardes negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: their freeing of ſubiects from their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and alliegance when it is written, <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect &amp;c.</hi> Their direct croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the written worde as, when it is ſaide: <hi>No man commeth to the father but by me,</hi> they ſay we haue many mediatours by whome we may come to the father beſides Chriſt: when it is ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> they ſay, if not chaſtly, yet charily, and find in one fiſh ponde of Gregory 6000 childrens skulls by that wicked charynes: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:6779:69"/>ſaith, <hi>You erre becauſe you knowne not the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> they ſay directly contrarie you will erre if you meddle with the ſcriptures: when the Lord ſaieth, <hi>when you haue done all ſay you are vnprofitable ſeruants;</hi> they ſay, we may doe workes of ſupererogation, more then we are bound, and ſo merit for others . Alſo when the Lord forbiddeth a luſting looke, their Pope giueth licence not onely to erect a ſtews wherein not long ſince were nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred 40000. harlots that paid a yeerely rent, and vpon the 12 day at night were ſeene goe into the Popes pallace 17. coaches full of curtizans. But (ô hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible) euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o practiſe the ſinne againſt nature, and not to be named, during the 3. hotte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths in the yeare, Iune, Iuly, Auguſt. Al which with many moe may giue any Chriſtian man or woman not finally forſaken of God and left to a reprobate mind, a true taſt of that Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed religion, and cauſe them iuſtly to reaſon thus: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Popery maintaineth flat Idolatrie diuers waies,therefore not true.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It alloweth other groſſe ſinnes forbidden of God, therefore not true.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It nuzleth the hart of man in ſecuritie, therefore not true. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> It robbeth the conſcience of comfort and hope by maintaining doubting,therefore not true.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> It deſtroieth the ordinance of God lawfull magiſtracy and loyall obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:6779:69"/>therefore not true. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> It flieth the light and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth darkeneſſe therefore not true, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> It ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it ſelfe and groweth by lies, falſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,ſlaunders, dreames, reuelations, counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit holineſſe and fained miracles, therefore not true. Deare Mother, open your eies, and regard your ſoule. Be as you ſhould be, wiſe without wilfulneſſe, zealous without ſuperſtition, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet to diſcerne, carefull to beware regarding God, prince, and countrie before any ſpirituall enchaunters whatſoeuer: yea regarding your ſelfe and my deare father, with vs your poore children, who riſe and fall with your well and ill doing. I am no enemie that begge this of you, but euen your owne bowells who haue liued in you, and neuer deſire to liue without you, your child, your own, by God and nature bound vnto you. O Mother behold my teares thinke of my heart, proſtrate before you vpon my face, I beg it for his ſake who gaue me to you; whoſe loue is life, whoſe trueth is ioy, whoſe power and goodneſſe is infinit to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them that honour him. Mine eies behold you for ſome worde of comfort, caſt me not away for Ieſus ſake without it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M.</speaker>
               <p>Deare child ariſe, &amp; let my ſilence now content thee, It ſhall not be long ere we talke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Your father co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth towards vs, whome
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:6779:70"/>I pray you goe meere, and let him not knowe as yet of our ſpeech. When he was turned fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her towards his father, ſhee caught the houſe vpon her, and into her cloſet ſhee went with haſt, where all bewaſhing her ſelfe with teares, ſhee brake out in this ſort. O my God and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious father, thou haſt raiſed out of mine owne bodie a teacher for me that I might not ſcorne him, and who by me receiued life concerning his bodie, he by thee hath offred me life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my ſoule, if I will receiue it. I cannot, I cannot denie his reaſons, I feele them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uince me, I haue no excuſe againſt ſuch trueth, and ſuch a teacher, but I am caught, I am caught, ô my God, if I will not damnably breake out of thy net againe, and runne deſperatly headlong vpon mine owne deſtruction. VVo is me that I ſo long haue erred from thy trueth harkning to the vaine inventions of mans braine. Thy word I knowe is trueth, and why ſhould not I ground my ſelfe and ſoule vpon it? Thy worde I heare is able to make me wiſe vnto ſaluation, and ſo can no writing of man. <hi>To the lavv and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the teſtimonie,</hi> ſaith thy Prophet, I nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and if they ſpeake not according to this, it is becauſe there is no light in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. VVho hath grounded vpon this rocke, and hath miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried? yet my ſoule knoweth how popery
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:6779:70"/>abhorreth this lantarne: we may not read it, we may not goe to Church to heare it, we may not haue it tranſlated for vs, but darknes, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that is ſtil the mother of devotion, though the holy ghoſt hath ſaid, <hi>Search the ſcriptures and be not children in vnderſtanding.</hi> Howe can this then be the true religion, the truth, the light, that forbiddeth al meanes of knowledge? They binde and burn, I cannot denie, the Saints of God, &amp; bathe themſelues in innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blood. All is hypocriſie and vain glorie, I ſee, I ſee, that ruleth amongſt them. O father ſtrengthen me, ô Sauiour pittie me, ô holy ghoſt confirme me and finiſh this worke begunne in me to the eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall praiſe of thy name, and the profitable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of others by my example that are abuſed and deceiued by theſe craftie iuglers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull workers, as I was. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
